Did you hear that?
Tu as entendu ?
They shut down the main reactor. We’ll be destroyed for sure.
Le réacteur est coupé ! On va être pulvérisés !
This is madness.
C’est de la folie pure !
We’re doomed.
Nous sommes perdus !
There’ll be no escape for the princess this time.
La princesse Leia ne peut s’échapper !
What’s that?
Qu’est-ce que c’est ?
R2-D2, where are you?
R2-D2, où es-tu ?
At last! Where have you been?
Enfin ! Où étais-tu ?
They’re heading in this direction. What are we going to do?
Ils arrivent ! Que faire ?
We’ll be sent to the spice mines of Kessel, or smashed into who knows what!
On va nous déporter ou nous envoyer à la casse !
Wait a minute. Where are you going?
Attends ! Où vas-tu ?
The Death Star plans are not in the main computer.
Les plans de l’Étoile de la Mort ne sont pas ici.
Where are those transmissions you intercepted?
Vous avez intercepté ces plans...
– What have you done with those plans? – We intercepted no transmissions.
– Qu’en avez-vous fait ? – Nous n’avons rien intercepté.
This is a consular ship. We’re on a diplomatic mission.
C’est un engin consulaire... en mission diplomatique.
If this is a consular ship, where is the ambassador?
Si c’est un vaisseau consulaire, où est l’ambassadeur ?
Commander, tear this ship apart until you’ve found those plans...
Fouillez cet engin, retrouvez les plans...
...and bring me the passengers! I want them alive!
et amenez-moi les passagers... Vivants !
There’s one. Set for stun.
Le rayon paralysant !
She’ll be all right. Inform Lord Vader we have a prisoner.
Elle n’a rien. Annoncez sa capture au seigneur Vador.
Hey! You’re not permitted in there. It’s restricted.
Il ne faut pas entrer là. C’est interdit !
You’ll be deactivated for sure.
On va te désactiver !
Don’t you call me a mindless philosopher, you overweight glob of grease!
Moi, un intellectuel ramolli ? Gros tas de cambouis !
Now come out before somebody sees you.
Sors, avant qu’on te voie !
“Secret mission”? What plans? What are you talking about? I’m not getting in there.
Quelle mission secrète ? Quels plans ? Que me racontes-tu ? Non, je n’entrerai pas !
I’m going to regret this.
Je vais le regretter !
– There goes another one. – Hold your fire.
– Un engin est parti ! – Ne tire pas...
There’s no life forms. It must have short-circuited.
y a pas d’être vivant à bord. Il y a eu un court-circuit.
That’s funny. The damage doesn’t look as bad from out here.
Les dégâts n’ont pas l’air importants, vus d’ici.
Are you sure this thing is safe?
Cet engin n’est pas dangereux ?
Darth Vader. Only you could be so bold.
Dark Vador ! Ce forfait porte votre marque !
The Imperial Senate will not sit still for this. When they hear you’ve attacked a diplomatic—
Le siège impérial saura que vous avez attaqué une mission.
Don’t act so surprised, Your Highness. You weren’t on any mercy mission this time.
Trêve de faux-semblants, Altesse. Ça, une mission de bienfaisance ?
Several transmissions were beamed to this ship by rebel spies.
Des espions rebelles vous ont transmis des messages.
I want to know what happened to the plans they sent you.
Où sont les plans qu’ils vous ont remis ?
I don’t know what you’re talking about.
Je ne sais de quoi vous parlez !
I’m a member of the Imperial Senate on a diplomatic mission to Alderaan.
Je suis membre du sénat, en mission à Alderaan.
You are part of the Rebel Alliance and a traitor.
Vous êtes liée aux rebelles. Vous avez trahi...
Take her away!
Emmenez-la !
Holding her is dangerous. If word of this gets out...
La garder est dangereux. Si on l’apprend...
...it could generate sympathy for the rebellion in the Senate.
le sénat peut se rallier à elle.
I’ve traced the rebel spies to her. Now she is my only link to finding their secret base.
La filière des rebelles remonte à elle. Elle seule peut nous mener à leur base.
– She’ll die before she’ll tell you anything. – Leave that to me.
– Elle préférera mourir ! – Je la ferai parler !
Send a distress signal and then inform the Senate that all aboard were killed.
Annoncez au sénat que son vaisseau est perdu corps et biens.
Lord Vader, the battle station plans are not aboard this ship...
Les plans de l’Étoile de la Mort ne sont pas à bord.
...and no transmissions were made.
Nul message n’a été envoyé.
An escape pod was jettisoned during the fighting, but no life forms were aboard.
Mais un engin de sauvetage a décollé, sans être vivant à bord.
She must have hidden the plans in the escape pod.
Elle a dû y cacher les plans.
Send a detachment down to retrieve them. See to it personally, Commander.
Formez une patrouille pour les récupérer. Vous m’en répondrez !
– There’ll be no one to stop us this time. – Yes, sir.
– Nul ne se mettra sur notre route ! – Bien, monsieur.
How did we get into this mess?
Comment est-on tombés dans ce pétrin ?
I really don’t know how.
J’y perds mon latin !
We seem to be made to suffer. It’s our lot in life.
Nous sommes faits pour souffrir... Voilà notre lot !
I’ve got to rest before I fall apart. My joints are almost frozen.
Reposons-nous ou je vais tomber en pièces. J’ai les jointures gelées.
What a desolate place this is!
Comme cet endroit est sinistre !
Where do you think you’re going?
Où vas-tu donc ?
Well, I’m not going that way.
Je n’irai pas par là.
It’s much too rocky. This way is much easier.
Il y a trop de rochers. De ce côté c’est plus facile.
What makes you think there are settlements over there?
Comment sais-tu qu’il y a un village là-bas ?
Don’t get technical with me.
Pas de mots techniques !
What mission? What are you talking about?
Quelle mission ? De quoi parles-tu ?
I’ve just about had enough of you.
Je t’ai assez vu !
Go that way. You’ll be malfunctioning within a day, you nearsighted scrap pile.
Va par là ! Tes circuits seront vite grippés, pauvre tas de ferraille myope !
And don’t let me catch you following me begging for help, because you won’t get it.
Et ne me suis pas en appelant à l’aide ! Je t’abandonne à ton sort !
No more adventures. I’m not going that way.
Non, assez d’aventures... Je n’irai pas par là.
That malfunctioning little twerp. This is all his fault.
Vilain nabot déréglé, tout ça est de sa faute.
He tricked me into going this way, but he’ll do no better.
Il m’a forcé à aller par ici... Mais il ne s’en tirera pas mieux que moi !
Wait! What’s that? A transport! I’m saved!
Tiens, que vois-je ? Un véhicule ! Je suis sauvé !
Over here! Hey! Hey!
Par ici ! Ohé ! Ohé !
Help! Please help!
Au secours ! Je vous en prie... au secours !
R2?
R2 ?
R2-D2, it is you! It is you!
R2-D2, c’est toi ! C’est bien toi !
Someone was in the pod. The tracks go off in this direction.
L’engin était habité, on voit des traces de pas.
Look, sir. Droids.
Ça vient d’un droïde.
Wake up! Wake up!
Réveille-toi !
We’re doomed.
Nous sommes perdus !
Do you think they’ll melt us down?
On va aller à la casse ?
Don’t shoot!
Ne tirez pas !
Will this never end?
Ça ne finira jamais ?
All right, fine. Let’s go.
Bon, allons-y.
Luke! Luke!
Luke ! Luke !
Luke, tell Uncle if he gets a translator, be sure it speaks Bocce.
Luke, dis à ton oncle d’acheter un traducteur de Bocce.
Doesn’t look like we have much of a choice, but I’ll remind him.
Il n’y a guère de choix ici mais je lui dirai.
Yeah, we’ll take that red one. No, not that one.
Je prends le rouge. Non, pas celui-là.
You, I suppose you’re programmed for etiquette and protocol.
Tu es programmé pour le protocole ?
Protocol? Why, it’s my primary function, sir. I am well-versed in all the customs—
C’est ma fonction principale. Je connais les coutumes de—
– I have no need for a protocol droid. – Of course you haven’t, sir.
– Je n’ai pas besoin de ça. – Certes pas, Monsieur.
Not in an environment such as this. That is why I have been programmed—
Ce milieu ne s’y prête guère ! Mais je sais aussi—
What I really need is a droid who understands the binary language of moisture vaporators.
Je cherche un traducteur du langage binaire des évaporateurs.
Vaporators? Sir, my first job was programming binary load lifters...
J’ai débuté comme programmateur de treuils binaires...
...very similar to your vaporators in most respects.
C’est le même principe.
– Can you speak Bocce? – Of course I can, sir. It’s like...
– Tu sais le Bocce ? – Bien sûr, c’est...
– ...a second language to me. I’m as fluent— – Yeah, all right. Shut up. I’ll take this one. Luke!
– ma seconde langue et— – Tais-toi ! Je le prends. Luke !
Take these two over to the garage, will you? I want them cleaned up before dinner.
Emmène-les au garage et nettoie-les.
But I was going into Tosche Station to pick up some power converters.
Je dois aller à Tosche pour les transfos !
You can waste time with your friends when your chores are done.
Tu iras t’amuser quand le travail sera fini.
– Now come on. Get to it. – All right. Come on.
– Allons, secoue-toi ! – Très bien. Viens.
And the red one. Come on.
Toi aussi, le rouge, viens !
Well, come on, red. Let’s go.
Alors, tu viens ?
– Uncle Owen! – Yeah?
– Oncle Owen. – Oui ?
This R2 unit has a bad motivator. Look.
Ce R2 a un défaut de motivateur !
Hey, what are you trying to push on us?
Tu me revends de la camelote !
Excuse me, sir, but that R2 unit is in prime condition, a real bargain.
Que Monsieur m’excuse, mais ce R2 est en parfait état. Une affaire en or !
Uncle Owen, what about that one?
Oncle Owen ! Et celui-là ?
What about that blue one? We’ll take that one.
Il marche, le bleu ? Je prends celui-là.
– Yeah, take this away. – You’ll be very pleased with that one, sir.
– Emportez-le. – Je suis certain que Monsieur sera content.
He really is in first-class condition. I’ve worked with him before.
Il est de premier ordre. J’ai déjà fait équipe avec lui.
Here he comes.
Il arrive.
Okay, let’s go.
Allons-y.
Now, don’t you forget this. Why I should stick my neck out for you...
N’oublie pas ça ! Pourquoi je me saigne aux quatre veines pour toi...
...is quite beyond my capacity.
ça me dépasse !
Thank the maker! This oil bath is going to feel so good.
Loué soit le Concepteur ! Ce bain d’huile est une bénédiction.
I’ve got such a bad case of dust contamination, I can barely move.
Je suis empoussiéré à mourir, je peux à peine bouger !
It just isn’t fair. Oh, Biggs is right. I’m never gonna get out of here.
Ce n’est vraiment pas juste ! Biggs a raison. Je ne partirai jamais d’ici !
– Is there anything I might do to help? – No. Not unless you can alter time...
– Puis-je être utile à Monsieur ? – Non, sauf si tu peux accélérer le temps...
...speed up the harvest, or teleport me off this rock.
ou m’aider à quitter ce rocher !
I don’t think so, sir. I’m only a droid, and not very knowledgeable about such things...
Hélas non, je ne suis qu’un droïde. Mes capacités sont limitées.
...not on this planet, anyway. As a matter of fact, I’m not even sure which planet I’m on.
En tout cas sur cette planète ! Au fait, j’ignore sur quelle planète je suis !
Well, if there’s a bright center to the universe, you’re on the planet that it’s farthest from.
Si l’univers a un centre, tu es sur une planète qui en est le plus loin.
– I see, sir. – You can call me Luke.
– Je vois, Monsieur. – Tu peux m’appeler Luke.
I see, Sir Luke.
Très bien, maître Luke.
Just Luke.
Luke tout court !
Hello.
Bonjour.
You’ve got a lot of carbon scoring here. Looks like you boys have seen a lot of action.
Tu as des traces de carbone... Vous avez eu des pépins ?
With all we’ve been through, sometimes I’m amazed...
On en a tant vu que je m’étonne...
...we’re in as good condition as we are, what with the rebellion and all.
d’être encore debout, avec cette rébellion !
You know of the rebellion against the Empire?!
La rébellion contre l’Empire ?
That’s how we came to be in your service, if you take my meaning, sir.
Elle nous vaut d’être ici.
– Have you been in many battles? – Several, I think.
– Tu as vu des batailles ? – Plusieurs... je crois.
Actually, there’s not much to tell. I’m not much more than an interpreter...
Je n’ai pas grand-chose à dire. Un interprète ne sait pas...
...and not very good at telling stories. Well, not at making them interesting, anyway.
raconter les histoires ou, du moins, les rendre intéressantes.
Well, my little friend, you’ve got something jammed in here real good.
Eh bien, mon petit ami, tu as quelque chose de bizarre coincé ici...
Were you on a Starcruiser or—
Étais-tu sur un croiseur interstellaire ou—
Help me, Obi-Wan Kenobi. You’re my only hope.
Au secours, Obi-Wan Kenobi, vous êtes mon seul espoir !
What’s this?
Qu’est-ce que c’est ?
“What is what”? He asked you a question. What is that?
Alors ? On t’a posé une question !
Help me, Obi-Wan Kenobi. You’re my only hope.
Au secours, Obi-Wan Kenobi, vous êtes mon seul espoir !
Oh. He says it’s nothing, sir. Merely a malfunction. Old data. Pay it no mind.
Il dit que ce n’est rien. De vieilles données sans importance.
Who is she? She’s beautiful.
Qui est-ce ? Elle est belle !
I’m afraid I’m not quite sure, sir.
Je n’en sais trop rien, Monsieur.
I think she was a passenger on our last voyage.
Elle était à bord de notre appareil.
A person of some importances, I believe. Our captain was attached to—
Une dame de qualité, je crois. Notre capitaine était—
Is there any more to this recording?
Il y a une suite ?
Behave yourself, R2. You’re going to get us into trouble.
Tiens-toi bien, tu vas nous attirer des ennuis !
It’s all right. You can trust him. He’s our new master.
Fais-lui confiance, c’est notre nouveau maître.
He says that he’s the property of Obi-Wan Kenobi...
Il dit qu’il appartient à Obi-Wan Kenobi...
...a resident of these parts, and it’s a private message for him.
qui habite cette planète. Ce message est pour lui seul.
Quite frankly, sir, I don’t know what he’s talking about.
Je n’y comprends vraiment rien.
Our last master was Captain Antilles. But with all we’ve been through...
Nous servions le capitaine Antilles. Après ce que nous avons traversé...
...this little R2 unit has become a bit eccentric.
R2 a les circuits dérangés.
Obi-Wan Kenobi. I wonder if he means old Ben Kenobi.
Je me demande s’il parle du vieux Ben Kenobi...
I beg your pardon, sir, but do you know what he’s talking about?
Monsieur sait-il de quoi il s’agit ?
Well, I don’t know anyone named Obi-Wan, but old Ben lives out beyond the Dune Sea.
Je ne connais personne qui s’appelle Obi-Wan, mais il y a Ben, qui vit derrière les dunes.
He’s kind of a strange old hermit.
Un vieil ermite bizarre.
I wonder who she is. Sounds like she’s in trouble.
Qui peut-elle être ? Elle semble en danger.
I better play back the whole thing.
Repassons tout le message.
He says the restraining bolt has short-circuited his recording system.
Il dit que le plot de sécurité bloque son décodeur.
He suggests that if you remove the bolt...
Selon lui, si Monsieur ôtait le plot...
...he might be able to play back the entire recording.
il pourrait repasser tout le message.
Hm? Oh, yeah. Well...
D’accord.
...I guess you’re too small to run away on me...
Petit comme tu es, tu ne te sauveras pas...
...if I take this off. Okay...
si je l’enlève. Bon.
There you go.
Et voilà.
Wait a minute. Where’d she go? Bring her back. Play back the entire message.
Où est-elle ? Ramène-la ! Repasse tout le message !
“What message”? The one you’ve just been playing!
« Quel message » ? Celui que tu as passé...
The one you’re carrying inside your rusty innards.
et que tu caches dans tes tripes rouillées !
Luke! Luke!
Luke ! Luke !
– All right, I’ll be right there, Aunt Beru. – I’m sorry, sir...
– Je viens tout de suite, Tante Beru ! – Je suis navré...
...but he appears to have picked up a slight flutter.
il semble avoir des parasites.
Here. See what you can do with him. I’ll be right back.
Essaie d’arranger ça, je vais revenir.
Just you reconsider playing that message for him.
Repasse-lui le message, je t’en supplie.
No, I don’t think he likes you at all.
Non, il ne t’aime pas.
No, I don’t like you, either.
Et je ne t’aime pas non plus !
You know, I think that R2 unit we bought might have been stolen.
Ce R2-D2 pourrait bien avoir été volé.
What makes you think that?
Pourquoi dis-tu ça ?
Well, I stumbled across a recording while I was cleaning him.
J’ai capté un message en le nettoyant.
He says he belongs to someone called Obi-Wan Kenobi.
Il appartiendrait à un certain Obi-Wan Kenobi.
I thought he might have meant old Ben. Do you know what he’s talking about?
Est-ce Ben ? Tu y comprends quelque chose ?
– I wonder if he’s related to Ben. – That wizard’s just a crazy old man.
– A-t-il un rapport avec Ben ? – Ce vieux sorcier est timbré.
Tomorrow, I want you to take that R2 unit to Anchorhead and have its memory erased.
Demain, emmène ce R2-D2 pour qu’on lui efface sa mémoire.
That’ll be the end of it. It belongs to us now.
Ça a assez duré... Il est à nous !
But what if this Obi-Wan comes looking for him?
Et si cet Obi-Wan vient le chercher ?
He won’t. I don’t think he exists anymore. He died about the same time as your father.
Il ne viendra pas. Non, il a dû mourir la même année que ton père.
– He knew my father? – I told you to forget it.
– Il a connu mon père ? – Oublie tout ça.
Your only concern is to prepare those new droids for tomorrow.
Mets au point ces droïdes pour demain.
In the morning, I want them up there on the south ridge...
Je veux les faire travailler...
– ...working on those condensers. – Yes, sir.
– sur les condensateurs. – Très bien.
I think those new droids are gonna work out fine.
Je crois que ces droïdes sont de bons éléments.
In fact, I, uh, was also thinking about our agreement...
Au fait... on était d’accord...
...about me staying on another season...
pour que je parte cette saison !
...and if these new droids do work out, I want to transmit my application...
S’ils sont rodés, je pourrai aller...
– ...to the academy this year. – You mean the next semester...
– à l’Académie. – Quoi, six mois...
– ...before the harvest? – Sure. There’s more than enough droids.
– avant la moisson ? – Oui, tu as assez de droïdes.
Harvest is when I need you the most. It’s only one season more.
J’ai besoin de toi pour la moisson. Reste encore une saison.
This year we’ll make enough on the harvest that I’ll be able to hire some more hands...
Ensuite, j’aurai de quoi embaucher des ouvriers...
...and then you can go to the academy next year. You must understand I need you here, Luke.
et tu iras à l’Académie. J’ai besoin de toi ici !
– But it’s a whole ’nother year! – Look, it’s only one more season.
– Ça fait toute une année ! – Juste une saison de plus !
Yeah, that’s what you said when Biggs and Tank left.
Tu l’as dit quand mes amis sont partis !
– Where are you going? – Looks like I’m going nowhere.
– Où vas-tu ? – Nulle part !
I have to go finish cleaning those droids.
Je vais nettoyer les droïdes.
Owen, he can’t stay here forever. Most of his friends have gone.
Il ne peut rester ici à jamais... ses amis sont partis !
– It means so much to him. – I’ll make it up to him next year. I promise.
– Et l’Académie est si importante ! – Je lui revaudrai ça l’an prochain... promis !
Luke’s just not a farmer, Owen. He has too much of his father in him.
Il est tout sauf un fermier, Owen. Il ressemble trop à son père.
That’s what I’m afraid of.
C’est bien ce qui me fait peur.
What are you doing hiding back there?
Pourquoi te caches-tu ?
It wasn’t my fault, sir. Please don’t deactivate me.
Ce n’est pas ma faute ! Ne me désactivez pas !
I told him not to go, but he’s faulty, malfunctioning.
Je lui ai dit de rester ! Mais il est tout déréglé...
– Kept babbling on about his mission. – Oh, no.
– et ne parle que de sa mission ! – Oh, non.
That R2 unit has always been a problem.
Ce R2 a toujours fait des siennes !
These astrodroids are getting quite out of hand.
Ces astro-droïdes sont intenables !
Even I can’t understand their logic at times.
Leur logique m’échappe !
How could I be so stupid? He’s nowhere in sight. Blast it!
J’ai été trop bête ! Je ne le vois nulle part... Quelle poisse !
– Pardon me, sir, but couldn’t we go after him? – It’s too dangerous...
– Si nous allions à sa recherche ? – Trop risqué la nuit...
...with all the Sand People around. We’ll have to wait until morning.
à cause des Hommes des Sables.
Luke! I’m shutting the power down.
Luke, je coupe le transfo !
All right! I’ll be there in a few minutes. Boy, am I gonna get it.
Je rentre dans une minute ! Je vais me faire incendier !
You know, that little droid’s gonna cause me a lot of trouble.
Ce robot va m’attirer des ennuis !
Oh, he excels at that, sir.
C’est un art où il est passé maître.
Have you seen Luke this morning?
Tu as vu Luke ce matin ?
He said he had some things to do before he started today, so he left early.
Il avait à faire, alors il est parti très tôt.
– Did he take those two new droids with him? – I think so.
– Avec les nouveaux droïdes ? – Oui, je crois.
Well, he better have those units in the south range...
J’espère qu’ils seront...
...repaired by midday, or there’ll be hell to pay.
au travail d’ici midi, sinon il va le sentir passer !
Lookit, there’s a droid on the scanner. Dead ahead.
Je vois un droïde sur l’écran, droit devant !
It might be our little R2 unit. Hit the accelerator!
C’est peut-être R2... Accélère à fond !
Hey, whoa! Just where do you think you’re going?
Arrête, où est-ce que tu t’en vas comme ça ?
Master Luke is your rightful owner now.
Monsieur est ton maître légitime.
We’ll have no more of this Obi-Wan Kenobi gibberish.
Ne me parle plus de cet Obi-Wan je ne sais qui !
And don’t talk to me of your mission, either. You’re fortunate he doesn’t blast you...
Ni de cette « mission » ! Estime-toi heureux qu’il ne...
– ...into a million pieces right here! – No. It’s all right, but I think we’d better go.
– te pulvérise pas ! – C’est bon, mais allons-y.
There are several creatures approaching from the southeast.
Il signale des êtres non identifiés au sud-est.
Sand People, or worse.
Des Hommes des Sables... ou pire !
Come on, let’s go have a look. Come on!
Allons voir... Venez ! Venez.
Well, there are two Banthas down there...
Je vois deux Banthas là-bas...
...but I don’t see any... Wait a second.
mais rien d’autre... Attendez !
They’re Sand People, all right. I can see one of them now.
Oui, des Hommes des Sables... j’en vois un !
Hello, there.
Bonjour, toi !
Come here, my little friend. Don’t be afraid.
Approche, mon petit ami, n’aie pas peur.
Oh, don’t worry. He’ll be all right.
Rassure-toi, il va s’en tirer.
Rest easy, son. You’ve had a busy day.
Tout doux, fils, tu as pris un vilain coup.
You’re fortunate to be all in one piece.
Une chance que tu sois en un seul morceau !
Ben? Ben Kenobi?
Ben ? Ben Kenobi ?
Boy, am I glad to see you.
Que je suis content de vous voir !
The Jundland Wastes are not to be traveled lightly.
Ce désert n’est pas sûr.
Tell me, young Luke, what brings you out this far?
Dis-moi, jeune Luke, qu’est-ce qui t’amène si loin ?
This little droid.
C’est à cause de ce droïde.
I think he’s searching for his former master, but I’ve never seen such devotion...
Il cherche son ancien maître. Je n’ai jamais vu...
...in a droid before.
un droïde si fidèle !
He claims to be the property of an Obi-Wan Kenobi.
Il dit appartenir à un certain Obi-Wan Kenobi.
Is he a relative of yours? Do you know who he’s talking about?
Est-ce un parent à vous ? Vous savez de quoi il parle ?
Obi-Wan Kenobi? Obi-Wan.
Obi-Wan Kenobi ? Obi-Wan.
Now, that’s a name I’ve not heard in a long time.
Voilà un nom que je n’ai pas entendu depuis bien longtemps.
A long time.
Bien longtemps !
I think my uncle knows him. He said he was dead.
Mon oncle l’a connu. Selon lui, il est mort.
Oh, he’s not dead. Not yet.
Il n’est pas mort ! Pas encore !
– You know him? – Well, of course I know him. He’s me.
– Vous le connaissez ? – Bien sûr, je le connais... C’est moi.
I haven’t gone by the name of Obi-Wan...
On ne m’a pas appelé Obi-Wan...
...since, oh, before you were born.
depuis bien avant ta naissance.
Well, then the droid does belong to you.
Alors ce droïde est à vous !
I don’t seem to remember ever owning a droid.
Je n’ai jamais possédé de droïde.
Very interesting.
C’est très intéressant.
I think we’d better get indoors. The Sand People are easily startled...
Il vaut mieux rentrer. Les Hommes des Sables ont eu peur...
...but they’ll soon be back, and in greater numbers.
mais ils vont revenir avec des renforts.
3PO.
3PO.
Where am I? I must have taken a bad step.
Où suis-je ? J’ai dû manquer une marche.
Can you stand? We’ve got to get out of here before the Sand People return.
Lève-toi, il faut filer avant leur retour.
I don’t think I can make it. You go on, Master Luke.
Je ne peux pas. Partez sans moi, maître Luke.
There’s no sense in you risking yourself on my account.
Ne risquez pas votre vie pour moi.
I’m done for.
Mon compte est bon.
– No, you’re not. What kind of talk is that? – Quickly. They’re on the move.
– Tu dis des bêtises ! – Vite, ils arrivent.
No, my father didn’t fight in the wars. He was a navigator on a spice freighter.
Mon père n’a pas fait la guerre. Il était sur un transport.
That’s what your uncle told you.
C’est ce que ton oncle t’a dit.
He didn’t hold with your father’s ideals. Thought he should have stayed here...
Il n’avait pas le même idéal. Selon lui, ton père aurait...
...and not gotten involved.
dû rester ici à l’abri.
– You fought in the Clone Wars? – Yes. I was once a Jedi knight...
– Vous avez fait la guerre ? – Oui. J’étais un chevalier Jedi autrefois...
...the same as your father.
comme ton père.
– I wish I’d known him. – He was the best starpilot in the galaxy...
– Je l’ai si peu connu... – Il était le meilleur astro-pilote de la galaxie.
...and a cunning warrior.
Et un habile tacticien...
I understand you’ve become quite a good pilot yourself.
On m’a dit que tu es toi-même un très bon pilote.
And he was a good friend. Which reminds me...
Il était aussi un ami. Ça me fait penser...
...I have something here for you.
J’ai quelque chose qui t’est destiné.
Your father wanted you to have this when you were old enough...
Ton père voulait que cela te revienne...
...but your uncle wouldn’t allow it.
mais ton oncle s’y est opposé.
He feared you might follow old Obi-Wan on some damn-fool idealistic crusade...
Il craignait que tu suives Obi-Wan dans quelque folle croisade idéaliste...
...like your father did.
comme ton père.
Sir, if you’ll not be needing me, I’ll close down for a while.
Si on n’a pas besoin de moi, puis-je m’éteindre ?
Sure. Go ahead.
Oui, débranche-toi.
– What is it? – Your father’s lightsaber.
– Qu’est-ce que c’est ? – Le sabre-laser de ton père.
This is the weapon of a Jedi knight.
L’arme des Jedi.
Not as clumsy or random as a blaster.
C’est moins grossier que le pistolaser !
An elegant weapon for a more civilized age.
L’arme noble et élégante d’une époque plus civilisée.
For over a thousand generations, the Jedi knights were the guardians...
Durant mille générations, les Jedi ont maintenu...
...of peace and justice in the old Republic...
la paix et la justice dans l’ancienne République.
...before the dark times... before the Empire.
Avant les jours sombres et l’avènement de l’Empire.
How did my father die?
Comment mon père est-il mort ?
A young Jedi named Darth Vader...
Un jeune Jedi, nommé Dark Vador...
...who was a pupil of mine until he turned to evil...
qui était mon disciple, s’est rallié au mal.
...helped the Empire hunt down and destroy the Jedi knights.
Il a aidé l’Empire à massacrer les chevaliers Jedi.
He betrayed and murdered your father.
Il a trahi et assassiné ton père.
Now the Jedi are all but extinct.
L’ordre Jedi a quasiment disparu.
Vader was seduced by the dark side of the Force.
Vador a été séduit par le côté obscur de la Force.
The Force?
La Force ?
The Force is what gives a Jedi his power.
C’est la Force qui donne au Jedi son pouvoir.
It’s an energy field created by all living things.
C’est un champ d’énergie créé par tout être vivant...
It surrounds us, penetrates us, it binds the galaxy together.
qui nous entoure, nous pénètre et unit la galaxie en un tout.
Now let’s see if we can’t figure out what you are, my little friend...
Essayons de savoir qui tu es, mon petit ami.
...and where you come from.
Et d’où tu viens...
– I saw part of a message he w— – I seem to have found it.
– J’ai vu une partie de message— – Je crois que j’ai trouvé.
General Kenobi, years ago you served my father in the Clone Wars.
Général Kenobi, vous avez servi mon père dans la Guerre des Clones.
Now he begs you to help him in his struggle against the Empire.
Il vous supplie de l’aider encore à combattre l’Empire.
I regret that I am unable to present my father’s request to you in person.
Je ne puis vous apporter sa requête moi-même.
But my ship has fallen under attack...
L’ennemi a pris mon vaisseau...
...and I am afraid my mission to bring you to Alderaan has failed.
et je ne peux vous amener à Alderaan.
I have placed information vital to the survival of the rebellion...
J’ai placé des informations vitales...
...into the memory systems of this R2 unit. My father will know how to retrieve it.
dans le mémorisateur de ce droïde R2-D2. Mon père saura les récupérer.
You must see this droid safely delivered to him on Alderaan.
Ce droïde doit lui parvenir intact à Alderaan.
This is our most desperate hour.
Notre situation est désespérée !
Help me, Obi-Wan Kenobi. You’re my only hope.
Au secours, Obi-Wan Kenobi, vous êtes mon seul espoir !
You must learn the ways of the Force if you’re to come with me to Alderaan.
Tu dois savoir maîtriser la Force si tu veux m’accompagner.
Alderaan? I’m not going to Alderaan.
À Alderaan ? Impossible !
I’ve got to get home. It’s late. I’m in for it as it is.
Je dois rentrer. Il est tard, ça va barder !
I need your help, Luke. She needs your help.
J’ai besoin de ton aide... et elle aussi !
I’m getting too old for this sort of thing.
Moi, je suis trop vieux pour aller me battre.
I can’t get involved. I’ve got work to do.
Je ne peux pas m’en mêler. J’ai trop de travail ici.
It’s not that I like the Empire. I hate it, but there’s nothing I can do about it right now.
Moi aussi je déteste l’Empire mais je ne peux rien faire maintenant !
– It’s all such a long way from here. – That’s your uncle talking.
– Et Alderaan est si loin ! – On croirait entendre ton oncle !
My uncle. How am I ever gonna explain this?
Flûte... mon oncle ! Comment lui expliquer ça ?
Learn about the Force, Luke.
Il faut acquérir la Force.
Look, I can take you as far as Anchorhead.
Je peux vous conduire à Anchorhead...
You can get a transport there to Mos Eisley or wherever you’re going.
et de là on vous emmènera à Mos Eisley ou ailleurs.
You must do what you feel is right, of course.
Bien sûr. Tu dois agir selon ta conscience.
Until this battle station is fully operational, we are vulnerable.
Tant qu’on n’est pas opérationnel on reste vulnérable.
The Rebel Alliance is too well equipped. They’re more dangerous than you realize.
Les rebelles sont bien équipés. Ils sont trop dangereux.
Dangerous to your starfleet, Commander... not to this battle station.
Dangereux pour vos chasseurs, mais pas pour l’Étoile de la Mort.
The rebellion will continue to gain support in the Imperial Senate—
La rébellion va gagner des partisans au sénat impérial—
The Imperial Senate will no longer be of any concern to us.
Le sénat impérial ne sera bientôt plus un obstacle.
I have just received word that the Emperor has dissolved the council permanently.
J’ai appris que l’Empereur a enfin dissous le conseil.
The last remnants of the old Republic have been swept away.
Les derniers vestiges de l’ancienne République sont balayés.
That’s impossible.
C’est impossible !
How will the Emperor maintain control without the bureaucracy?
Gouverner sans les fonctionnaires ?
The regional governors now have direct control over their territories.
Les gouverneurs régionaux ont toute autorité sur leurs territoires.
Fear will keep the local systems in line...
La peur... voilà ce qui bâillonnera les systèmes séditieux.
– ...fear of this battle station. – And what of the rebellion?
– La peur de l’Étoile de la Mort ! – Et les rebelles ?
If the rebels have obtained a complete technical readout of this station...
S’ils ont les plans secrets de l’Étoile de la Mort...
...it is possible, however unlikely, that they might find a weakness and exploit it.
il n’est pas impossible qu’ils trouvent une faille !
The plans you refer to will soon be back in our hands.
Nous récupérerons bientôt ces plans.
Any attack made by the rebels against this station...
S’attaquer à cette base...
...would be a useless gesture, no matter what technical data they’ve obtained.
serait une folie, même s’ils en possèdent les plans.
This station is now the ultimate power in the universe.
C’est l’engin de guerre le plus puissant de l’univers.
I suggest we use it.
Mettons-le à l’épreuve !
Don’t be too proud of this technological terror you’ve constructed.
Ne vous fiez pas trop à cet épouvantail technologique.
The ability to destroy a planet is insignificant...
La capacité de détruire une planète n’est rien...
...next to the power of the Force.
en comparaison de la Force !
Don’t try to frighten us with your sorcerer’s ways, Lord Vader.
Cessez de brandir votre baguette de sorcier !
Your sad devotion to that ancient religion...
Votre foi dans l’ancienne religion...
...has not helped you conjure up the stolen data tapes...
n’a pas fait réapparaître les plans volés...
...or given you clairvoyance enough to find the rebels’ hidden fortr—
et ne vous a pas révélé la base secrète des rebelles—
I find your lack of faith disturbing.
Votre manque de foi me consterne.
Enough of this. Vader, release him.
Cela suffit ! Vador, laissez-le !
As you wish.
À votre guise.
This bickering is pointless.
Ces chamailleries sont absurdes.
Lord Vader will provide us with the location of the rebel fortress...
Seigneur Vador, pendant que vous localisez la base rebelle...
...by the time this station is operational.
nous mettrons l’Étoile de la Mort sur le pied de guerre.
We will then crush the rebellion with one swift stroke.
Et puis nous écraserons la rébellion d’un seul coup.
It looks like the Sand People did this, all right.
Les Hommes des Sables ont fait le coup...
Look. There’s gaffi sticks, Bantha tracks.
on voit leurs traces.
It’s just, I’ve never heard of them hitting anything this big before.
C’est un bien gros gibier pour eux !
They didn’t... but we are meant to think they did.
Ce n’est pas eux. C’est une ruse pour nous le faire croire.
These tracks are side-by-side. Sand People always ride single file...
Ces traces sont côte à côte, or les Hommes vont en file indienne...
...to hide their numbers.
pour cacher leur nombre.
These are the same Jawas that sold us R2 and 3PO.
Ces Jawas nous ont vendu les 2 droïdes !
And these blast points, too accurate for Sand People.
Et ces impacts ! Les Hommes des Sables ne tirent pas aussi bien.
Only Imperial stormtroopers are so precise.
Seules les Troupes de la Mort de l’Empire ont cette précision.
But why would Imperial troops want to slaughter Jawas?
Mais pourquoi massacrer des Jawas ?
If they traced the robots here, they may have learned who they sold them to...
S’ils ont retrouvé la trace des robots...
...and that would lead them back... home!
ça va les conduire à nous, à la maison !
Wait, Luke! It’s too dangerous!
Attends, Luke. C’est trop dangereux !
Uncle Owen! Aunt Beru!
Oncle Owen. Tante Beru.
And now, Your Highness, we will discuss the location of your hidden rebel base.
Et maintenant, Altesse, vous allez me dire où est la base secrète de la rébellion.
There’s nothing you could have done, Luke, had you been there.
Tu n’aurais rien pu faire, Luke.
You’d have been killed, too, and the droids would now be in the hands of the Empire.
Tu aurais été tué, toi aussi. Et les droïdes auraient été capturés.
I want to come with you to Alderaan.
Je veux vous accompagner à Alderaan.
There’s nothing for me here now. I want to learn the ways of the Force...
Plus rien ne me retient ici. Je veux acquérir la Force...
...and become a Jedi like my father.
pour être un Jedi.
Mos Eisley spaceport.
Voici l’astroport de Mos Eisley.
You will never find a more wretched hive of scum and villainy.
C’est le repaire le plus infâme des renégats et des malandrins.
We must be cautious.
Il faut être prudent.
– How long have you had these droids? – About three or four seasons.
– Depuis quand ces droïdes sont à vous ? – Depuis trois ou quatre saisons.
They’re up for sale if you want them.
On les vend, vous en voulez ?
– Let me see your identification. – You don’t need to see his identification.
– Montrez vos papiers. – Inutile de voir ses papiers.
– We don’t need to see his identification. – These aren’t the droids you’re looking for.
– Inutile de voir ses papiers... – Ce ne sont pas ces droïdes que vous cherchez.
These aren’t the droids we’re looking for.
Ce ne sont pas ces droïdes...
He can go about his business.
Il peut s’en aller.
– You can go about your business. – Move along.
– Vous pouvez vous en aller. – Circulez...
Move along.
Circulez.
I can’t abide those Jawas. Disgusting creatures!
Je ne peux pas sentir ces Jawas ! Ils sont immondes !
Go on, go on.
Va-t’en, va-t’en.
I can’t understand how we got by those troops. I thought we were dead.
Comment a-t-on pu passer ? Je nous voyais fusillés !
The Force can have a strong influence on the weak-minded.
La Force peut influencer les esprits faibles.
Do you really think we’re gonna find a pilot here that’ll take us to Alderaan?
Vous croyez qu’on va trouver un pilote ?
Most of the best freighter pilots are to be found here...
On trouve les meilleurs astro-pilotes ici...
...only watch your step. This place can be a little rough.
mais sois vigilant. Les rixes sont courantes.
I’m ready for anything.
Je suis prêt à tout.
Come along, R2.
Viens, R2.
– Hey! We don’t serve their kind here. – What?
– On sert pas ceux-là ici. – Quoi ?
Your droids, they’ll have to wait outside. We don’t want them here.
Vos droïdes... Qu’ils sortent, j’en veux pas ici !
Why don’t you wait out by the speeder? We don’t want any trouble.
Attends dehors, évitons les ennuis.
I heartily agree with you, sir.
Je suis plus que d’accord avec Monsieur !
I’ll have one of those.
Je voudrais un verre de ça...
– He doesn’t like you. – I’m sorry.
– Tu lui plais pas ! – Je suis désolé.
I don’t like you, either.
Tu me plais pas non plus !
You just watch yourself. We’re wanted men. I have the death sentence on 12 systems.
Alors fais bien attention ! On est recherchés. Je suis condamné à mort dans 12 systèmes !
I’ll be careful.
Je ferai attention.
– You’ll be dead! – This little one’s not worth the effort.
– Tu vas y passer ! – Ce garçon est inoffensif.
Come, let me get you something.
Je vous offre un verre.
I’m all right.
Ça va.
Chewbacca here is first mate on a ship that might suit us.
Chewbacca est copilote d’un engin qui pourrait nous convenir.
I don’t like the look of this.
Tout ceci ne me plaît guère !
Han Solo. I’m captain of the Millennium Falcon.
Je suis Han Solo, capitaine du Faucon Millénium.
Chewie here tells me you’re looking for passage to the Alderaan system.
Il parait que vous voulez aller à Alderaan ?
Yes, indeed, if it’s a fast ship.
Oui, si votre appareil est rapide.
Fast ship? You’ve never heard of the Millennium Falcon?
Vous connaissez pas le Faucon Millénium ?
Should I have?
Je devrais ?
It’s the ship that made the Kessel run in less than 12 parsecs.
Il a fait le raid sur Kessel en moins de 12 parsecs !
I’ve outrun Imperial starships. Not the local bulk cruisers, mind you.
Je bats de vitesse les engins impériaux ! Je parle pas des croiseurs...
I’m talking about the big Corellian ships now.
mais des nouveaux vaisseaux corelliens !
She’s fast enough for you, old man.
Oui, je suis assez rapide, vieux !
– What’s the cargo? – Only passengers...
– Quelle cargaison ? – Seulement des passagers.
Myself, the boy, two droids...
Moi-même, ce garçon, deux droïdes...
...and no questions asked.
et pas de questions indiscrètes !
What is it, some kind of local trouble?
Vous avez des ennuis dans ce bled ?
Let’s just say we’d like to avoid...
Disons que je souhaite éviter...
...any Imperial entanglements.
que l’Empire s’intéresse trop à nous.
Well, that’s the real trick, isn’t it?
C’est un autre genre de truc, ça, non ?
And it’s gonna cost you something extra.
Faut compter un extra.
Ten thousand, all in advance.
Dix mille, payés d’avance !
Ten thousand?
Dix mille ?
We could almost buy our own ship for that!
Le prix d’un engin neuf !
– But who’s gonna fly it, kid? You? – You bet I could.
– Et qui va le piloter, p’tit gars ? Toi ? – Et comment !
I’m not such a bad pilot myself. We don’t have to sit here and listen...
Je sais piloter ! Allons-nous-en...
We can pay you two thousand now...
Je peux verser 2000 maintenant...
...plus fifteen when we reach Alderaan.
et 15000 de plus en arrivant à Alderaan.
Seventeen, huh?
Ça fait 17000 ?
Okay, you guys got yourselves a ship.
D’accord. Je vous loue mon zinc !
We’ll leave as soon as you’re ready. Docking Bay 94.
On partira dès que vous serez prêts. Hangar 94.
Ninety-four.
94.
Looks like somebody’s beginning to take an interest in your handiwork.
Il y a des gens qui s’intéressent à vos petits exploits.
All right. We’ll check it out.
Bon. On va vérifier.
Seventeen thousand!
Dix-sept mille !
Those guys must really be desperate. This could really save my neck.
Ils doivent être dans le pétrin ! Ça me sauve la vie !
Get back to the ship, get it ready.
Va préparer l’appareil.
You’ll have to sell your speeder.
Il faut vendre ton engin.
That’s okay. I’m never coming back to this planet again.
Tant pis. Je ne reviendrai plus sur cette planète !
Yes, Greedo. As a matter of fact, I was just going to see your boss.
Oui, Greedo... j’allais voir ton patron !
Tell Jabba that I’ve got his money.
Dis à Jabba que j’ai son argent.
Yeah, but this time I’ve got the money.
Cette fois j’ai le fric pour te payer.
I don’t have it with me. Tell Jabba—
Je n’ai pas l’argent sur moi. Dis à Jabba—
Even I get boarded sometimes. Do you think I had a choice?
J’ai été arraisonné ! Tu crois que j’avais le choix ?
Over my dead body.
Faudra d’abord me tuer !
Yes, I’ll bet you have.
Ça m’étonne pas de toi !
Sorry about the mess.
Désolé de laisser des saletés !
Her resistance to the mind probe is considerable.
Sa résistance au mental-scope est remarquable.
It’ll be some time before we can extract any information from her.
Il faudra du temps pour lui tirer des renseignements.
The final checkout is completed.
Tout est au point...
All systems are operational. What course shall we set?
L’Étoile de la Mort est opérationnelle. Quel cap devons-nous suivre ?
Perhaps she would respond to an alternative form of persuasion.
La princesse réagira peut-être mieux à d’autres arguments.
What do you mean?
Comment ça ?
I think it is time we demonstrated the full power of this station.
Il est temps de montrer la puissance de cette base.
– Set your course for Alderaan. – With pleasure.
– Cap sur Alderaan ! – Avec plaisir.
Lock the door, R2.
Bloque la porte, R2 !
All right, check this side of the street.
Vérifiez l’autre côté de la rue.
The door’s locked. Move on to the next one.
C’est verrouillé, voyons plus loin.
I would much rather have gone with Master Luke than stay here with you.
J’aurais dû suivre maître Luke !
I don’t know what all this trouble is about, but I’m sure it must be your fault.
J’ignore ce qui se passe, mais c’est sûrement ta faute !
You watch your language.
Et ne jure pas comme ça !
All right. Give it to me. I’ll take it.
D’accord, c’est vendu...
Look at this. Ever since the XP-38 came out, they just aren’t in demand.
Depuis la sortie du XP-38, mon speeder ne vaut plus rien !
It’ll be enough.
Cette somme suffira.
If the ship’s as fast as he’s boasting, we ought to do well.
Si son engin va aussi vite qu’il le prétend, tout ira bien.
What a piece of junk!
Il est bon pour la casse !
She’ll make .5 past light speed.
Il fait 1,5 fois la vitesse-lumière !
She may not look like much, but she’s got it where it counts, kid.
Il n’est pas bien beau mais il en a dans le ventre.
I’ve made a lot of special modifications myself.
J’ai fait plein de modifications spéciales.
But we’re a little rushed, so if you’ll just get on board we’ll get outta here.
Mais si vous voulez bien monter à bord... il est temps de filer !
Hello, sir.
Bonjour, monsieur.
Which way?
De quel côté ?
All right, men, load your weapons.
Allons-y, l’arme au poing !
Stop that ship! Blast them!
Arrêtez cet engin ! Feu !
Chewie, get us out of here!
Mets la gomme !
Oh, my. I’d forgotten how much I hate space travel.
J’avais oublié... je déteste les vols spatiaux !
Looks like an Imperial cruiser.
Un croiseur !
Our passengers must be hotter than I thought. Try and hold ’em off.
Nos passagers valent de l’or !
Angle the deflector shields while I make the calculations for the jump to light speed.
Règle le déflecteur, je calcule le saut en vitesse-lumière.
Stay sharp. There’s two more coming in. They’re gonna try and cut us off.
En voilà deux autres, ils viennent par le travers !
Why don’t you outrun ’em? I thought you said this thing was fast!
Je croyais ce coucou imbattable ?
Watch your mouth, kid, or you’re gonna find yourself floating home.
Tais-toi, sinon tu rentres à pied !
We’ll be safe enough once we make the jump to hyperspace.
Ça ira dès qu’on passera dans l’hyperespace.
Besides, I know a few maneuvers. We’ll lose ’em.
Je sais comment les semer !
Here’s where the fun begins.
La fête commence !
How long before you can make the jump to light speed?
Quand passe-t-on la barre ?
It’ll take a few moments to get the coordinates from the navicomputer.
Le temps de définir les navi-composantes.
Are you kidding? At the rate they’re gaining?
Ils gagnent sur nous !
Traveling through hyperspace ain’t like dustin’ crops, boy!
Piloter dans l’hyperespace, c’est pas pulvériser des moissons !
Without precise calculations, we’d fly right through a star...
Une erreur et on écorche une étoile !
...or bounce too close to a supernova...
Ou on frôle une supernova...
...and that would end your trip real quick, wouldn’t it?
et la balade est vite terminée !
– What’s that flashing? – We’re losing a deflector shield.
– Le clignotant ! – Le déflecteur est réglé !
Go strap yourselves in. I’m gonna make the jump to light speed.
Attachez-vous, on passe en vitesse-lumière.
We’ve entered the Alderaan system.
Le système d’Alderaan est en vue.
Governor Tarkin. I should have expected to find you holding Vader’s leash.
Gouverneur Tarkin ! Vous voilà bien sûr dans l’ombre de Vador !
I recognized your foul stench when I was brought on board.
J’ai senti votre odeur méphitique en montant à bord !
Charming to the last.
Charmante... jusqu’à la fin !
You don’t know how hard I found it, signing the order to terminate your life.
Dire que j’ai hésité à signer votre condamnation à mort !
I’m surprised you had the courage to take the responsibility yourself.
Cette responsabilité ne vous a pas fait peur ?
Princess Leia, before your execution, I would like you to be my guest...
Princesse, en prélude à votre exécution, je vous convie...
...at a ceremony that will make this battle station operational.
à la cérémonie de notre première action de guerre.
No star system will dare oppose the Emperor now.
Nul système n’osera plus défier l’Empereur !
The more you tighten your grip, Tarkin...
Plus vous resserrerez votre étau...
...the more star systems will slip through your fingers.
et plus de systèmes vous échapperont !
Not after we demonstrate the power of this station.
Pas quand ils verront notre puissance !
In a way, you have determined the choice of the planet that will be destroyed first.
C’est vous qui avez inspiré le choix de la planète qui sera détruite la première.
Since you are reluctant to provide us with the location of the rebel base...
Puisque vous refusez de nous dire où est la base rebelle...
...I have chosen to test this station’s destructive power...
j’ai décidé de tester notre puissance de destruction...
...on your home planet of Alderaan.
sur votre planète Alderaan !
No! Alderaan is peaceful. We have no weapons. You can’t possibly—
Non ! Alderaan est pacifique... sans armement—
You would prefer another target? A military target? Then name the system.
Vous préférez un objectif militaire ? Alors... où est votre base ?
I grow tired of asking this, so it will be the last time.
Cela devient lassant ! Pour la dernière fois...
Where is the rebel base?
Où est la base rebelle ?
Dantooine.
Dantooine.
– They’re on Dantooine. – There. You see, Lord Vader?
– À Dantooine. – Vous voyez, Vador...
She can be reasonable. Continue with the operation. You may fire when ready.
elle peut être raisonnable ! Poursuivez l’opération... Feu !
– What? – You’re far too trusting.
– Quoi ? – Vous êtes si naïve !
Dantooine is too remote to make an effective demonstration, but don’t worry.
Dantooine est trop loin pour servir d’exemple...
We will deal with your rebel friends soon enough.
mais les rebelles auront bientôt leur tour !
Commence primary ignition.
Paré pour la mise à feu !
Are you all right? What’s wrong?
Ça ne va pas ? Que se passe-t-il ?
I felt a great disturbance in the Force...
J’ai senti une grande perturbation dans la Force !
...as if millions of voices suddenly cried out in terror...
Comme si des millions de voix avaient hurlé de peur...
...and were suddenly silenced. I fear something terrible has happened.
et s’étaient soudain éteintes... Un drame horrible a dû arriver.
You’d better get on with your exercises.
Continue tes exercices.
Well, you can forget your troubles with those Imperial slugs.
Les Impériaux ne nous embêteront plus.
I told you I’d outrun them.
Je vous avais dit que je les sèmerais !
Don’t everybody thank me at once.
Ne me remerciez pas tous à la fois !
Anyway, we should be at Alderaan about 0200 hours.
On sera en vue d’Alderaan vers deux heures.
Now be careful, R2.
Attention, R2 !
He made a fair move. Screaming about it can’t help you.
Bien joué ! Ce n’est pas en beuglant que tu t’en sortiras !
Let him have it. It’s not wise to upset a Wookiee.
Contrarie pas le Wookiee.
But, sir, nobody worries about upsetting a droid.
Et contrarier un droïde, on a le droit ?
That’s ’cause a droid don’t pull people’s arms out of their sockets...
Un droïde n’arrache pas le bras de son adversaire...
...when they lose. Wookiees are known to do that.
quand il perd. Mais les Wookiees ne s’en privent pas !
I see your point, sir.
J’en prends bonne note.
I suggest a new strategy, R2. Let the Wookiee win.
R2, modifie ta stratégie ! Laisse gagner le Wookiee !
Remember, a Jedi can feel the Force flowing through him.
Un Jedi sent la Force filtrer à travers son corps.
– You mean it controls your actions? – Partially, but it also obeys your commands.
– Elle dirige les actions ? – En partie... mais elle sait aussi obéir.
Hokey religions and ancient weapons are no match...
Ce credo à la noix et ce sabre démodé...
...for a good blaster at your side, kid.
ça vaut pas un pistolaser !
You don’t believe in the Force, do you?
Tu ne crois pas à la Force ?
Kid, I’ve flown from one side of this galaxy to the other.
J’ai volé d’un coin de la galaxie à l’autre...
I’ve seen a lot of strange stuff, but I’ve never seen anything...
et j’ai vu des trucs fumants, mais rien qui prouve...
...to make me believe there’s one all-powerful force controlling everything.
qu’il y a un pouvoir capable de diriger tout l’univers.
There’s no mystical energy field controls my destiny.
Et c’est pas une force mystique qui dirigera ma vie à moi !
It’s all a lot of simple tricks and nonsense.
Tout ça c’est des trucs, des balivernes !
I suggest you try it again, Luke.
J’aimerais que tu essaies encore, Luke.
This time, let go your conscious self...
Cette fois, oublie ton être conscient...
...and act on instinct.
et laisse agir ton instinct.
With the blast shield down, I can’t even see.
Avec la visière ? Je ne vois rien !
How am I supposed to fight?
Je ne peux pas me battre !
Your eyes can deceive you. Don’t trust them.
Le regard peut tromper, ne t’y fie pas.
Stretch out with your feelings.
Laisse aller ton intuition.
– You see? You can do it. – I call it luck.
– Tu vois... tu y arrives ! – Un coup de chance !
In my experience, there’s no such thing as luck.
Dans mon expérience la chance n’existe pas !
Look, good against remotes is one thing. Good against the living, that’s something else.
Contre un gadget télécommandé, bon... Mais contre un homme... c’est pas aussi facile !
Looks like we’re coming up on Alderaan.
On arrive à Alderaan.
You know, I did feel something. I could almost see the remote.
Je sentais la sphère. Je la voyais presque !
That’s good. You’ve taken your first step into a larger world.
C’est bien... Tu as fait ton premier pas dans un univers plus vaste.
– Yes? – Our scout ships have reached Dantooine.
– Oui ? – Nos hommes sont à Dantooine.
They found the remains of a rebel base...
On a vu les traces d’une base...
...but they estimate that it has been deserted for some time.
qui parait désertée depuis longtemps.
They are now conducting an extensive search of the surrounding systems.
On fait des recherches intensives dans les systèmes voisins.
She lied. She lied to us!
Elle a menti ! Elle nous a menti !
I told you she would never consciously betray the rebellion.
Je savais que jamais elle ne trahirait.
Terminate her... immediately.
Qu’on l’exécute... immédiatement !
Stand by, Chewie. Here we go. Cut in the sublight engines.
On arrive... enclenche les rétrofusées.
What the...?
Qu’est-ce que...
We’ve come out of hyperspace into a meteor shower.
On est pris dans une pluie de météorites !
Some kind of asteroid collision. It’s not on any of the charts.
Y a rien sur la carte !
– What’s going on? – Our position’s correct, except no Alderaan.
– Que se passe-t-il ? – On y est... mais y a pas d’Alderaan !
– What do you mean? Where is it? – That’s what I’m trying to tell you, kid.
– Où est-elle ? – C’est ce que j’essaie de te dire.
It ain’t there. It’s been totally blown away.
Elle est pas là, je te dis ! Elle s’est volatilisée !
– What? How? – Destroyed by the Empire.
– Quoi ? Comment ? – Détruite... par l’Empire !
The entire starfleet couldn’t destroy the whole planet.
Leur flotte n’y arriverait pas !
It would take a thousand ships with more firepower than I’ve—
Il faudrait mille engins super-puissants et—
There’s another ship coming in.
Voilà un appareil !
– Maybe they know what happened. – It’s an Imperial fighter.
– Ils savent peut-être. – Un chasseur impérial.
– It followed us! – No. It’s a short-range fighter.
– Il nous a suivis. – Il n’a pas ce rayon d’action.
There aren’t any bases around here. Where did it come from?
Y a aucune base par ici !
It sure is leaving in a big hurry. If they identify us, we’re in big trouble.
Il a l’air drôlement pressé ! S’il nous a identifiés, ça va chauffer !
Not if I can help it. Chewie, jam its transmissions.
Brouille sa radio !
It would be as well to let it go. It’s too far out of range.
Laissez-le, il est hors de portée.
Not for long.
Pas pour longtemps !
A fighter that size couldn’t get this deep into space on its own.
Un tel engin ne se risquerait pas seul dans l’espace.
He must have gotten lost, been part of a convoy or something.
Il s’est peut-être égaré.
Well, he ain’t gonna be around long enough to tell anybody about us.
Je lui laisserai pas le temps d’aller prévenir ses copains.
Look at him. He’s heading for that small moon.
Il se dirige vers cette lune !
I think I can get him before he gets there. He’s almost in range.
Je le rattraperai avant qu’il y arrive.
That’s no moon.
Ce n’est pas une lune.
– It’s a space station. – It’s too big to be a space station.
– C’est une base spatiale ! – C’est bien trop grand !
I have a very bad feeling about this.
J’ai un mauvais pressentiment !
Turn the ship around.
Faites demi-tour !
Yeah. I think you’re right. Full reverse! Chewie, lock in the auxiliary power.
Vous avez raison... Machine arrière ! Bloque les auxiliaires !
Chewie, lock in the auxiliary power!
Chewie, bloque les réacteurs auxiliaires !
Why are we still moving towards it?!
On continue d’avancer !
We’re caught in a tractor beam. It’s pulling us in!
On est attirés par un rayon !
– There’s got to be something you can do! – There’s nothing I can do about it, kid.
– Trouve quelque chose ! – Rien à faire !
I’m full power. I’m gonna have to shut down. They’re not gonna get me without a fight.
Je suis au maxi, ça va casser ! Je vais me bagarrer !
You can’t win, but there are alternatives to fighting.
Vous perdrez... mais il y a d’autres façons de l’emporter.
Clear Bay 327.
Dégagez la baie 327.
We’re opening the magnetic field.
On ouvre le champ magnétique !
To your stations! Come with me.
À vos postes. Vous, venez avec moi !
Close all outboard shields.
Fermez les panneaux de sortie.
– Yes? – We’ve captured a freighter...
– Oui ? – On a pris un engin...
...entering the remains of the Alderaan system.
près des restes d’Alderaan.
Its markings match those of a ship that blasted its way out of Mos Eisley.
Il a l’indicatif d’un engin pirate qui a fui de Mos Eisley.
They must be trying to return the stolen plans to the princess.
Ils veulent apporter les plans de l’Étoile de la Mort à Leia !
She may yet be of some use to us.
Elle peut encore servir !
Unlock 1, 5, 7, and 9. Release charge.
Ouvrez 1, 5, 7 et 9. Levez l’écran.
There’s no one on board, sir.
Il n’y a personne.
According to the log, the crew abandoned ship right after takeoff.
L’équipage a abandonné le bord.
It must be a decoy, sir. Several of the escape pods have been jettisoned.
Plusieurs engins de sauvetage manquent.
– Did you find any droids? – No, sir.
– A-t-on trouvé des droïdes ? – Non, monsieur.
If there were any on board, they must also have jettisoned.
S’il y en avait, ils ont été largués.
Send a scanning crew aboard. I want every part of this ship checked.
Faites fouiller cet appareil de bord à bord.
Yes, sir.
Oui, monsieur.
I sense something... a presence I’ve not felt since...
Je subodore quelque chose, une présence que je n’ai pas sentie depuis...
Get me a scanning crew in here on the double. I want every part of this ship checked.
Envoyez une équipe de dépistage. Vérifiez le vaisseau de fond en comble.
Boy, it’s lucky you had these compartments.
Pratiques, ces compartiments !
I use them for smuggling. I never thought I’d be smuggling myself in ’em.
Pour la contrebande, oui... je pensais pas m’y cacher moi-même !
This is ridiculous. Even if I could take off...
C’est ridicule ! Si on décolle...
– ...I’d never get past the tractor beam. – Leave that to me.
– le rayon nous reprendra. – Fiez-vous à moi.
Damn fool, I knew that you were gonna say that.
Il est fou ! Je savais qu’il dirait ça !
Who’s the more foolish, the fool or the fool who follows him?
Qui est le plus fou ? Le fou... ou alors le fou qui le suit ?
The ship’s all yours. If the scanners pick up anything, report it immediately.
Si vos compteurs repèrent quelque chose à bord, prévenez-moi.
All right, let’s go.
Allons-y.
Hey, down there!
Eh, en bas !
Could you give us a hand with this?
Vous pouvez nous donner un coup de main ?
TK-421, why aren’t you at your post?
TK-421, pourquoi n’êtes-vous pas à votre poste ?
TK-421, do you copy?
TK-421, vous me recevez ?
Take over. We’ve got a bad transmitter. I’ll see what I can do.
Une panne d’émetteur, je vais régler ça.
You know, between his howling and your blasting everything in sight...
Entre lui qui hurle et toi qui mitrailles...
...it’s a wonder the whole station doesn’t know we’re here.
on sera bientôt repérés !
Bring ’em on! I’d prefer a straight fight to all this sneakin’ around.
Qu’ils viennent donc ! Je préfère me bagarrer que me planquer !
We’ve found the computer outlet, sir.
On a le terminal !
Plug in. He should be able to interpret the entire Imperial network.
Branche R2. Décodons le schéma de l’Étoile de la Mort.
He says he’s found the main controls to the power beam that’s holding the ship here.
Il a localisé la commande du rayon qui empêche le décollage.
He’ll try to make the precise location appear on the monitor.
Il va la projeter sur l’écran.
I don’t think you boys can help. I must go alone.
Nul ne peut m’aider. Je dois agir seul.
Whatever you say. I’ve done more than I bargained for on this trip already.
Je n’insiste pas ! J’ai déjà fait plus que ma part !
I want to go with you.
Je vais avec vous.
Be patient, Luke. Stay and watch over the droids.
Patience, tu dois veiller sur les droïdes.
– But he can— – They must be delivered safely...
– Mais— – S’ils n’arrivent pas intacts...
...or other star systems will suffer the same fate as Alderaan.
d’autres subiront le même sort qu’Alderaan.
Your destiny lies along a different path from mine.
Ta destinée suit un autre chemin que la mienne.
The Force will be with you... always.
La Force est avec toi... à tout jamais !
You said it, Chewie. Where did you dig up that old fossil?
Tu as bien raison, vieux ! Où as-tu débusqué ce vieux fossile ?
Ben is a great man.
Ben est épatant !
– Yeah, great at getting us into trouble. – I didn’t hear you give any ideas.
– Pour attirer les ennuis ! – Quelle est ton idée ?
Well, anything’s better than just hangin’ around waiting for ’em to pick us up.
De pas attendre qu’on vienne nous pincer !
Who do you think—
Pour qui tu—
– What is it? – I’m afraid I’m not quite sure, sir.
– Qu’est-ce qu’il y a ? – Je n’en sais trop rien, Monsieur.
He says “I’ve found her” and keeps repeating “She’s here.”
Il répète : « Je l’ai trouvée, elle est là ! »
Well, who... who has he found?
Qui a-t-il trouvé ?
– Princess Leia. – The princess? She’s here?!
– La princesse Leia ! – La princesse est ici ?
– Princess?! – Where? Where is she?
– La princesse ? – Où est-elle ?
Princess?! What’s going on?
Qu’est-ce qui se passe ici ?
Level 5, Detention Block AA-23.
Niveau 5, Bloc AA-23.
I’m afraid she’s scheduled to be terminated.
Elle doit être exécutée !
Oh, no! We’ve got to do something!
Il faut la tirer de là !
– What are you talking about? – The droids belong to her.
– Explique-toi ! – Les droïdes sont à elles.
She’s the one in the message. We gotta help her.
C’est elle qui était dans le message ! Sauvons-la !
Now look, don’t get any funny ideas. The old man wants us to wait right here.
Te monte pas la tête ! Le vieux veut qu’on l’attende.
But he didn’t know she was here. Just find a way back into that detention block.
Il ignore qu’elle est là ! Comment arrive-t-on aux cellules ?
– I’m not going anywhere. – They’re going to execute her.
– Moi je vais nulle part ! – Ils vont l’exécuter !
Look, a few minutes ago, you said you didn’t want to just wait here to be captured.
Il y a un instant tu refusais d’attendre ici...
Now, all you want to do is stay?
Alors ?
Marching into the detention area is not what I had in mind.
Mon idée n’était pas d’envahir les cellules !
– But they’re gonna kill her! – Better her than me!
– Mais on va la tuer ! – Mieux vaut elle que moi !
She’s rich.
Elle est riche !
– Rich? – Mm-hmm. Rich, powerful.
– Riche ? – Oui, riche... puissante !
Listen, if you were to rescue her, the reward would be...
Si on la sauve il y aura une récompense...
– What? – Well, more wealth than you can imagine.
– Combien ? – Plus que tu ne peux imaginer !
– I don’t know, I can imagine quite a bit. – You’ll get it.
– Mon imagination est sans limite ! – Tout ce que tu veux !
– I better. – You will.
– Sans blague ? – Je te jure !
All right, kid. You better be right about this.
Bien, p’tit gars... j’espère que c’est vrai !
– All right. – What’s your plan?
– Bon. – Quel est ton plan ?
3PO, hand me those binders there, will you?
Passe-moi ces menottes, là-bas.
Okay...
D’accord.
Now... I’m gonna put these on you.
Je vais te les mettre et...
Okay Han, you... you put those on.
D’accord... Han, mets-les toi-même.
Don’t worry, Chewie. I think I know what he has in mind.
T’en fais pas, je devine son plan.
Master Luke, sir, pardon me for asking...
Maître Luke, pardonnez cette question...
...but what should R2 and I do if we’re discovered here?
mais que ferons-nous si on nous trouve ici ?
– Lock the door. – And hope they don’t have blasters.
– Ferme à clé ! – Et prie le Ciel qu’ils n’aient pas de pistolasers !
That isn’t very reassuring.
Ce n’est guère rassurant !
517 to scanner control.
517 à contrôle scanner.
I can’t see a thing in this helmet.
On n’y voit rien avec ce casque !
– This is not gonna work. – Why didn’t you say so before?
– Ça ne marchera pas ! – Fallait le dire avant.
I did say so before.
J’ai pas arrêté de le dire !
Where are you taking this... thing?
Où allez-vous avec cette... chose ?
Prisoner transfer from Cell Block 1138.
On transfère ce prisonnier du Bloc 1138.
I wasn’t notified. I’ll have to clear it.
On ne m’a pas prévenu. Attendez que je vérifie.
– Look out! He’s loose! – He’ll tear us all apart!
– Il s’est détaché ! – Il va nous dépecer !
Look out!
Attention.
We’ve got to find out which cell this princess of yours is in.
Voyons dans quelle cellule ta petite princesse est bouclée.
Here it is... 2187. You go and get her. I’ll hold them here.
Voilà... numéro 2187... Va la chercher. Je m’occupe des autres.
Uh, had a slight weapons malfunction, but, uh, everything’s perfectly all right now.
Rien... une arme mal réglée, mais... c’est réparé, maintenant. Tout baigne !
We’re fine... We’re all fine here now. Thank you. How are you?
Tout va bien... merci... Et vous, ça va ?
We’re sending a squad up.
Je vous envoie une escouade.
Give us a few minutes to lock it down. Uh, large leak, very dangerous.
Donnez-nous quelques minutes pour colmater... Une grosse fuite, c’est dangereux !
Who is this? What’s your operating number?
Qui est là ? Quel est votre code de service ?
Boring conversation anyway... Luke! We’re gonna have company!
Rasante, cette conversation ! Luke, on va avoir de la visite !
Aren’t you a little short for a stormtrooper?
Vous êtes petit pour un commando !
Huh? Oh, the uniform.
Oh, l’uniforme !
I’m Luke Skywalker. I’m here to rescue you.
Je suis Luke Skywalker... Venez !
– You’re who? – I’m here to rescue you.
– Vous êtes qui ? – Je viens vous sauver...
I’ve got your R2 unit. I’m here with Ben Kenobi.
Le R2 est ici, et Ben !
– Ben Kenobi?! Where is he? – Come on!
– Où ça ? – Venez.
– He is here. – Obi-Wan Kenobi?
– Il est ici. – Obi-Wan Kenobi ?
– What makes you think so? – A tremor in the Force.
– Qu’est-ce qui vous fait croire cela ? – Des remous dans la Force !
The last time I felt it was in the presence of my old master.
Je ne les ai jamais sentis qu’en présence de mon ancien maître.
Surely he must be dead by now.
Il est sûrement mort, depuis le temps !
Don’t underestimate the Force.
Ne sous-estimez pas la Force !
The Jedi are extinct. Their fire has gone out of the universe.
Les Jedi ont disparu. Leur fluide s’est tari dans tout l’univers.
You, my friend, are all that’s left of their religion.
Vous êtes le dernier tenant de leur religion.
Yes.
Oui.
We have an emergency alert in Detention Block AA-23.
On signale une alerte dans le bloc de détention AA-23.
The princess? Put all sections on alert.
La princesse ? Alertez toutes les sections !
Obi-Wan is here. The Force is with him.
Obi-Wan est à bord ! La Force est avec lui !
If you’re right, he must not be allowed to escape.
S’il est là, il ne faut pas qu’il s’échappe !
Escape is not his plan. I must face him alone.
Il n’en a pas l’intention. Je dois l’affronter seul !
Get behind me!
Reste derrière moi !
Watch your left. They went down the cell bay.
Ils sont dans le couloir des cellules !
Can’t get out that way.
On peut pas passer !
Looks like you managed to cut off our only escape route.
Vous avez coupé la seule issue !
Maybe you’d like it back in your cell, Your Highness.
Vous regrettez votre cellule, Altesse ?
– C-3PO, C-3PO! – Yes, sir?
– C-3PO ! C-3PO ! – Oui, monsieur ?
Are there any other ways out of the cell bay? We’ve been cut off!
Il y a une autre sortie ? Ils ont coupé le passage !
What was that? I didn’t copy.
Je ne te reçois pas !
I said all systems have been alerted to your presence, sir.
Leurs systèmes de sécurité vous ont repéré, Monsieur.
The main entrance seems to be the only way in or out.
Il n’y a qu’une seule entrée.
All other information on your level is restricted.
Le reste est secret à votre niveau.
Open up in there! Open up in there!
Ouvrez, là-dedans !
Oh, no!
Oh, non.
There isn’t any other way out!
Il n’y a pas d’autre passage.
I can’t hold them off forever! Now what?!
On ne va pas tenir ! Que fait-on ?
This is some rescue! You came in here, and you didn’t have a plan for getting out?
Joli sauvetage ! Vous n’aviez aucun plan ?
– He’s the brains, sweetheart! – Well, I didn’t...
– Le cerveau c’est Luke, chérie ! – Eh bien, je ne...
– What the hell are you doing? – Somebody has to save our skins.
– Qu’est-ce qui vous prend ? – Il faut bien que je vous tire de là !
Into the garbage chute, flyboy.
Tous dans le conduit à ordures !
Get in there!
Entrez !
Get in there, you big furry oaf! I don’t care what you smell.
Saute, gros macaque mité ! Tant pis si ça pue !
Get in there, and don’t worry about it.
Saute et t’en fais pas pour le reste !
Wonderful girl!
Épatante, cette fille !
Either I’m going to kill her, or I’m beginning to like her.
Ou je la tue ou je tombe amoureux !
Get in there!
Va là-dedans.
The garbage chute was a really wonderful idea.
La fosse à ordures, quelle merveilleuse idée !
What an incredible smell you’ve discovered!
Exquis, ce parfum que vous nous offrez !
Let’s get out of here.
Il faut sortir d’ici.
– Get away from there. – No, wait!
– Ôte-toi de là. – Non, attends.
Will you forget it? I already tried it! It’s magnetically sealed.
J’ai déjà essayé ! La fermeture est magnétique !
Put that thing away! You’re gonna get us all killed!
Posez cette arme, vous allez nous tuer !
Absolutely, Your Worship.
Avec joie !
Look, I had everything under control till you led us down here!
Tout allait bien avant que vous nous colliez là-dedans !
You know, it’s not gonna take ’em long to figure out what happened to us!
Ils nous auront vite repérés !
It could be worse.
Ça pourrait être pire !
– It’s worse. – There’s something alive in here.
– Le voilà, le pire ! – Y a un truc qui gigote !
– That’s your imagination. – Something just moved past my leg.
– C’est ton imagination ! – Non, ça bouge contre ma jambe !
Look! Did you see that?
Vous avez vu ça ?
What?
Quoi ?
Kid! Luke!
Petit ! Luke !
Luke! Luke, grab hold of this!
Luke, accrochez-vous à ça !
Blast it, will you? My gun’s jammed.
Tire ! Mon arme est enrayée !
– Where? – Anywhere!
– Où est-il ? – Tout autour de moi !
Help him! What happened?
Aidez-le ! Que s’est-il passé ?
I don’t know. It just let go of me and disappeared.
J’en sais rien. Il m’a lâché et il a disparu.
I’ve got a bad feeling about this.
Tout ça ne me dit rien qui vaille !
– The walls are moving! – Don’t just stand there!
– Les murs bougent ! – Il faut les bloquer !
Help me!
Aidez-moi.
Wait a minute!
Une minute.
3PO! Come in, 3PO!
3PO ! Tu me reçois ?
Where could he be?
3PO ! Où peut-il être ?
Take over. See to him.
Prenez le relais.
Look, there.
Attention ! Là-dedans !
They’re madmen!
Ils sont fous !
They’re heading for the prison level. If you hurry, you might catch them.
Ils vont vers les cellules ! Vite, rattrapez-les !
Follow me.
Suivez-moi.
You stand guard.
Toi, monte la garde ici.
Come on.
Viens.
All this excitement has overrun the circuits in my counterpart here.
Toute cette agitation a surchauffé mon équipier.
If you don’t mind, I’d like to take him down to maintenance.
Puis-je l’emmener à l’atelier pour le faire réviser ?
All right.
Très bien.
3PO! Come in, 3PO!
3PO. Réponds, 3PO.
– Get on top! – I can’t!
– Essayez de monter ! – Je ne peux pas.
Where could he be?! 3PO! 3PO, will you come in!
Où est-il passé ? 3PO, veux-tu répondre.
They aren’t here. Something must have happened to them.
Ils ne sont pas là ! Qu’est-il arrivé ?
See if they’ve been captured. Hurry!
Vérifie, ils sont peut-être prisonniers. Vite.
One thing’s for sure. We’re all gonna be a lot thinner.
Ce qui est sûr, c’est qu’on va maigrir un grand coup !
– Get on top of it. – I’m trying.
– Allez, grimpez ! – Je fais ce que je peux !
Thank goodness they haven’t found them! Where could they be?
Ils n’ont pas été pris ! Mais alors où sont-ils ?
Use the comlink?
Quoi, quel intercom ?
Oh, my. I forgot. I turned it off.
Oh, j’avais oublié ! Je l’ai coupé !
Are you there, sir?
C’est maître ?
3PO?!
3PO ?
– We’ve had some problems. – Will you shut up and listen to me?!
– On a eu des ennuis et... – Tais-toi et écoute !
Shut down all the garbage mashers on the detention level, will ya?!
Coupe tous les broyeurs à notre niveau !
Do you copy!? Shut down all the garbage mashers on the detention level!
Coupe les broyeurs qui sont à notre niveau !
No! Shut them all down. Hurry!
Coupe tout, vite !
What?
Quoi ?
Listen to them. They’re dying, R2!
Tu les entends ? Ils sont en train de mourir !
Curse my metal body! I wasn’t fast enough. It’s all my fault! My poor master.
Maudite soit ma carcasse de ferraille. C’est ma faute ! Mon pauvre maître !
We’re all right! You did great! Hey! Open the pressure maintenance hatch...
Tout va bien ! Tu as gagné ! Débranche la fermeture du caisson !
...on unit number... where are we? 3263827!
C’est le numéro 3263827 !
If we can just avoid any more female advice, we ought to be able to get outta here.
Si les bonnes femmes s’en mêlent pas, on peut s’en tirer !
Well, let’s get moving.
Dépêchons-nous.
Where are you going?
Où est-ce que tu vas ?
No, wait! They’ll hear!
Ils vont entendre !
Come here, you big coward. Chewie, come here.
Reviens, gros trouillard ! Chewie, viens là.
Listen...
Écoutez.
...I don’t know who you are or where you came from...
J’ignore qui vous êtes et d’où vous venez...
...but from now on, you do as I tell you, okay?
mais désormais, faites ce que je vous dis, vu ?
Look, Your Worshipfulness, let’s get one thing straight.
Et vous, Votre Splendeur, comprenez-moi bien !
I take orders from just one person... me!
La seule personne à qui j’accepte d’obéir, c’est moi !
It’s a wonder you’re still alive.
Je m’étonne de vous voir en vie !
Will somebody get this big walking carpet out of my way?
Débarrassez-moi de cette carpette ambulante !
No reward is worth this!
Tout l’or du monde ne vaut pas ça !
– Give me regular reports, please. – Right.
– Gardez le contact ! – D’accord.
– Do you know what’s going on? – Maybe it’s another drill.
– Tu sais ce qui se passe ? – Bah, un exercice...
You seen that new VT-16?
Tu as vu le nouveau VT-16 ?
Yeah. Some of the other guys were telling me about it.
Oui. Les gars m’en parlaient.
They say it’s... it’s quite a thing to see.
J’ai entendu dire qu’il était génial.
What was that?
Qu’est-ce que c’est ?
Ah, it’s nothing. Outgassing. Don’t worry about it.
Rien... y a du statique, t’en fais donc pas !
– There she is. – C-3PO? Do you copy?
– On y est enfin ! – 3PO, tu me reçois ?
Yes, sir.
Oui, monsieur.
– Are you safe? – For the moment.
– Tout va bien ? – Pour l’instant.
We’re in the main hangar across from the ship.
On est dans le hangar, en face de l’engin.
– We’re right above you. Stand by. – You came in that thing?!
– On est juste au-dessus. – Vous êtes venus avec ce truc ?
– You’re braver than I thought! – Nice! Come on.
– Vous êtes brave ! – Délicieuse ! Venez.
It’s them! Blast them!
C’est eux. Tire.
– Get back to the ship! – Where are you going? Come back!
– Montez à bord ! – Où vas-tu ?
– He certainly has courage. – What good will it do us if he gets himself killed?
– Il a du courage ! – Ça nous avancera à quoi s’il se fait tuer ?
Come on.
Venez !
I think we took a wrong turn.
On n’a pas dû tourner où il fallait !
There’s no lock!
Comment verrouiller ?
– That oughta hold them for a while. – Quick! We’ve got to get across.
– Ça tiendra un moment. – Il faut traverser.
– Find the controls that extend the bridge. – I think I just blasted it.
– Où est la commande de la passerelle ? – Je l’ai bousillée !
They’re coming through!
Ils arrivent !
Here, hold this.
Prenez ça.
Here they come.
Les voilà !
For luck.
Pour porter chance !
We think they may be splitting up. They may be on Level 5 and 6 now, sir.
Ils se séparent. Ils sont aux niveaux 5 et 6 maintenant, monsieur.
Where could they be?
Où sont-ils donc ?
Open the blast doors!
Rouvrez le passage !
I’ve been waiting for you, Obi-Wan. We meet again at last.
Je vous attendais, Obi-Wan. Enfin nous nous retrouvons !
The circle is now complete.
La boucle est bouclée !
When I left you, I was but the learner. Now I am the master.
Jadis j’étais votre disciple. Aujourd’hui je suis le maître.
Only a master of evil, Darth.
Le maître des forces du mal, Vador !
Your powers are weak, old man.
Vos pouvoirs s’estompent, vieillard !
You can’t win, Darth. If you strike me down...
Tu ne peux gagner ! Si tu me terrasses...
...I shall become more powerful than you can possibly imagine.
je deviendrai plus puissant que tu ne peux l’imaginer.
You should not have come back.
Vous n’auriez pas dû revenir !
Didn’t we just leave this party?
La fête n’est pas finie ?
– What kept you? – We, uh, ran into some old friends.
– Où étiez-vous ? – Oh, on a vu des amis !
– The ship all right? – It seems okay, if we can get to it.
– Le zinc n’a rien ? – Ça va, mais faut y arriver !
I just hope the old man got the tractor beam out of commission.
J’espère que le vieux a réussi !
Look!
Regardez.
Come on, R2, we’re going.
Vite, allons-y !
Now’s our chance! Go!
Voilà notre chance !
– Come on! – Come on! Come on!
– Allez !
– Luke, it’s too late! – Blast the door, kid!
– Il est trop tard ! – Bloque la porte, p’tit gars !
Run, Luke, run!
Cours, Luke ! Cours !
I hope that old man got that tractor beam out of commission...
Si le vieux n’a pas coupé le rayon...
...or this is gonna be a real short trip. Okay, hit it!
on n’ira pas loin ! Filons !
We’re coming up on their sentry ships. Hold them off.
Voilà des chasseurs !
Angle the deflector shields while I charge up the main guns.
Tâche de les semer, j’arme les tourelles.
I can’t believe he’s gone.
Je ne peux croire qu’il nous ait quittés...
There wasn’t anything you could have done.
Vous ne pouviez l’aider.
Come on, buddy. We’re not out of this yet.
Amène-toi. On n’en est pas sortis !
You in, kid? Okay, stay sharp.
Tu es branché, p’tit gars ? Ouvre l’œil !
Here they come.
Les voilà !
They’re coming in too fast!
Ils sont trop rapides !
– We’ve lost the lateral controls! – Don’t worry. She’ll hold together.
– Le contrôle est touché ! – Vous inquiétez pas, ça va tenir !
Hear me, baby? Hold together.
Compris, bébé ? Tiens bon !
– Got him! I got him! – Great, kid! Don’t get cocky.
– Je l’ai eu ! – Bravo ! Mais n’attrape pas la grosse tête !
There’s still two more of them out there!
Il y en a encore là-bas !
– That’s it! We did it! – We did it!
– Ça y est ! On a gagné ! – On a gagné !
Help! I think I’m melting! This is all your fault!
Au secours, je fonds ! C’est ta faute, R2 !
Are they away?
Ils ont décollé ?
They’ve just made the jump into hyperspace.
Oui, ils ont franchi la barre de l’hyperespace.
You’re sure the homing beacon is secure aboard their ship?
L’émetteur de repérage a été fixé sur leur appareil ?
I’m taking an awful risk, Vader. This had better work.
Je prends un très gros risque, Vador ! Vous m’en répondrez !
Not a bad bit of rescuing, huh?
Du beau boulot, ce décollage, non ?
You know, sometimes I amaze even myself.
Il m’arrive encore de m’épater moi-même !
That doesn’t sound too hard.
Ça ne m’étonne pas de vous !
They let us go. It’s the only explanation for the ease of our escape.
Non, on nous a laissé fuir ! Voilà pourquoi il a été si facile de partir.
– Easy? You call that easy? – They’re tracking us.
– Vous appelez ça facile ! – Ils nous suivent.
Not this ship, sister.
Pas ce zinc, fillette !
At least the information in R2 is still intact.
En tout cas, on a sauvé les informations de R2 !
– What’s so important? What’s he carrying? – The technical readouts of that battle station.
– C’est si important ? Qu’est-ce que c’est ? – Le diagramme technique de l’Étoile de la Mort.
I only hope that when the data’s analyzed, a weakness can be found.
Espérons qu’en l’analysant on trouvera une faille.
– It’s not over yet. – It is for me, sister.
– Tout n’est pas encore fini ! – C’est fini pour moi, fillette !
Look, I ain’t in this for your revolution, and I’m not in it for you, Princess.
Je me fiche de la rébellion et de vous aussi, princesse !
I expect to be well paid. I’m in it for the money.
Être bien payé, c’est tout ce qui m’intéresse.
You needn’t worry about your reward.
N’ayez crainte, vous serez payé !
If money is all that you love, then that’s what you’ll receive.
Si c’est pour l’argent, vous n’aurez rien d’autre !
Your friend is quite a mercenary. I wonder if he really cares about anything...
Votre ami n’est qu’un mercenaire. Je crois qu’il n’aime rien...
...or anybody.
ni personne !
I care!
Moi c’est différent !
So...
Alors...
– What do you think of her, Han? – I’m trying not to, kid.
– Qu’est-ce que tu penses d’elle ? – J’essaie de pas penser à elle !
Good.
Tant mieux !
Still, she’s got a lot of spirit.
Cela dit... elle a du cran !
I don’t know. What do you think? You think a princess and a guy like me—
Et toi, qu’en penses-tu ? Tu crois qu’elle et moi—
No.
Non.
You’re safe. When we heard about Alderaan, we feared the worst.
Vous êtes sauvée ! Nous avons craint le pire.
We have no time for sorrows, Commander. You must use the information in this R2 unit...
Nous pleurerons plus tard ! Les informations du R2...
...to help plan the attack. It’s our only hope.
dicteront notre tactique. C’est notre seul espoir.
– Yes. – We’re approaching the planet Yavin.
– Oui. – La planète Yavin est en vue.
The rebel base is on a moon on the far side. We are preparing to orbit the planet.
La base rebelle est sur une lune, du côté distant. Nous nous mettons sur orbite.
The battle station is heavily shielded, and carries a firepower...
L’Étoile de la Mort est bien protégée. Sa puissance de feu...
...greater than half the starfleet.
surpasse celle de toute la flotte impériale.
Its defenses are designed around a direct large-scale assault.
Elle est fortifiée pour repousser un assaut en force.
A small, one-man fighter should be able to penetrate the outer defense.
Mais des chasseurs monoplaces pourraient sans doute percer les défenses extérieures.
Pardon me for asking, sir, but what good are snub fighters going to be against that?
Que peut faire un engin léger contre un tel géant ?
Well, the Empire doesn’t consider a small, one-man fighter...
L’Empire s’estime invulnérable aux chasseurs légers...
...to be any threat, or they’d have a tighter defense.
sinon ses défenses rapprochées seraient plus élaborées.
An analysis of the plans provided by Princess Leia...
L’analyse des plans rapportés par la princesse...
...has demonstrated a weakness in the battle station.
a révélé que la base a un vice dans sa conception.
The approach will not be easy.
Mais l’approche sera difficile.
You’re required to maneuver straight down this trench...
Il s’agit de suivre cette tranchée...
...and skim the surface to this point.
en rase-mottes jusqu’à ce point-là.
The target area is only two meters wide.
La cible n’a que deux mètres de diamètre.
It’s a small thermal exhaust port right below the main port.
C’est une bouche d’aération située au bas d’une tour.
The shaft leads directly to the reactor system.
Ce conduit mène tout droit au réacteur central.
A precise hit will start a chain reaction, which should destroy the station.
Un coup au but déclencherait une réaction en chaîne qui détruirait la base.
Only a precise hit will set up a chain reaction.
Seul un tir précis peut déclencher l’explosion.
The shaft is ray-shielded, so you’ll have to use proton torpedoes.
Il faut utiliser des torpilles à proton.
– That’s impossible, even for a computer. – It’s not impossible.
– Même un ordinateur échouerait ! – C’est faisable !
I used to bull’s-eye womp rats in my T-16 back home.
Je tirais les rats volants à 800 mètres avec mon T-16...
They’re not much bigger than two meters.
et ils ne font pas 2 mètres !
Then man your ships, and may the Force be with you.
À vos postes ! Et que la Force soit avec vous !
Orbiting the planet at maximum velocity.
Nous sommes sur orbite à vitesse maximum.
The moon with the rebel base will be in range in 30 minutes.
La base rebelle sera à portée de feu dans 30 minutes.
This will be a day long remembered. It has seen the end of Kenobi...
Ce jour restera gravé à tout jamais. Il a vu la fin d’Obi-Wan Kenobi...
...and will soon see the end of the rebellion.
et il verra bientôt la fin de la rébellion !
All flight crews, man your stations.
Toutes les équipes de vol, à vos postes.
So... you got your reward and you’re just leaving, then?
Alors... tu as été payé et tu tires ta révérence ?
That’s right. Yeah.
Eh oui, p’tit gars !
I’ve got some old debts I’ve got to pay off with this stuff.
J’ai des vieilles dettes à liquider.
And even if I didn’t, you don’t think I’d be fool enough to stick around here, do you?
En dehors de ça, je suis pas assez fou pour rester ici !
Why don’t you come with us? You’re pretty good in a fight. We could use you.
Viens avec nous ! Tu te bats pas mal, ça peut servir !
Come on. Why don’t you take a look around?
Voyons, sers-toi de tes yeux !
You know what’s about to happen, what they’re up against.
Tu sais bien ce qui va arriver, ce qui nous menace !
They could use a good pilot like you. You’re turning your back on them.
C’est un atout, un pilote comme toi... et tu t’en vas ?
What good’s a reward if you ain’t around to use it?
Ce fric servira à quoi si j’y reste ?
Besides, attacking that battle station ain’t my idea of courage.
Et attaquer cette base, c’est pas du courage...
It’s more like... suicide.
c’est plutôt un suicide !
All right. Well, take care of yourself, Han.
Très bien. Prends bien soin de toi...
I guess that’s what you’re best at, isn’t it?
c’est ce que tu sais faire de mieux !
Hey, Luke.
Hé, Luke.
May the Force be with you.
Que la Force soit avec toi !
What are you looking at? I know what I’m doing.
Fais pas cette tête ! Je sais ce que je fais !
All pilots to your stations.
Pilotes, à vos postes.
– What’s wrong? – Oh, it’s Han.
– Qu’y a-t-il ? – C’est Han...
I don’t know. I really thought he’d change his mind.
J’étais tellement certain qu’il changerait d’avis.
He’s got to follow his own path. No one can choose it for him.
Il doit suivre sa propre route, nul ne peut décider pour lui.
I only wish Ben were here.
Je voudrais tant que Ben soit ici.
Open main launch tubes.
Ouvrez les tubes de lancement.
Main launch tubes opening, sir.
Tubes de lancement ouverts !
Hey, this R2 unit of yours seems a bit beat up. You want a new one?
Votre R2 a l’air mal en point. J’en mets un autre ?
Not on your life. That little droid and I have been through a lot together.
Pas question ! Lui et moi on en a vu de drôles !
You okay, R2?
Ça va, R2 ?
Good.
Bon.
Gold squadron, begin takeoff procedure.
Escadron d’Or, entamez la procédure de décollage.
Hang on tight, R2. You’ve got to come back.
Tiens bon la rampe, R2 ! Il faut que tu reviennes !
You wouldn’t want my life to get boring, would you?
Tu as envie que je m’ennuie tout seul ?
Luke, the Force will be with you.
Luke, la Force sera avec toi !
Standby alert. Death Star approaching.
L’Étoile de la Mort est en vue.
Estimated time to firing range, 15 minutes.
L’ennemi sera à portée dans 15 minutes.
– All wings report in. – Red 10 standing by.
– Tous au rapport. – Rouge 10, prêt.
– Red Seven standing by. – Red Three standing by.
– Rouge 7, prêt. – Rouge 3, prêt.
– Red Six standing by. – Red Nine standing by.
– Rouge 6, prêt. – Rouge 9, prêt.
– Red Two standing by. – Red 11 standing by.
– Rouge 2, prêt. – Rouge 11, prêt.
Red Five standing by.
Rouge 5, prêt.
Lock S-foils in attack position.
Enclenchez les ailerons d’attaque.
– We’re passing through their magnetic field. – Hold tight.
– On entre dans le champ magnétique. – Tenez bon !
Switch your deflectors on. Double front.
Sortez les déflecteurs. Front double.
– Look at the size of that thing! – Cut the chatter, Red Two.
– Regardez. Elle est énorme ! – Assez bavardé, Rouge 2.
Accelerate to attack speed.
Accélérez à fond.
– This is it, boys. – Red Leader, this is Gold Leader.
– On y est, les gars ! – Leader Rouge, ici Leader d’Or.
– I copy, Gold Leader. – We’re starting for the target shaft now.
– Je vous reçois. – On pique vers l’objectif.
We’re in position. I’m going to cut across the axis and try and draw their fire.
Je vais couper l’axe pour attirer leur feu.
– Heavy fire, boss, 23 degrees. – I see it. Stay low.
– Une batterie à 23 degrés ! – Volez en rase-mottes.
This is Red Five. I’m going in.
Ici Rouge 5, je pique.
Luke, pull up!
Luke, grimpe !
– Are you all right? – I got a little cooked, but I’m okay.
– Ça va, Luke ? – Je sens le roussi mais ça va.
We count 30 rebel ships, Lord Vader...
Il y a 30 appareils rebelles.
...but they’re so small, they’re evading our turbolasers.
Ils passent sous nos turbo-lasers !
We’ll have to destroy them ship to ship. Get the crews to their fighters.
Abattez-les au corps à corps. Faites décoller les chasseurs.
Watch yourself. There’s a lot of fire coming from the right side of that deflection tower.
Attention. Il y a une batterie à droite de la tour !
– I’m on it. – I’m going in. Cover me, Porkins.
– Je la vois. – Je m’en charge. Couvre-moi, Porkins.
I’m right with you, Red Three.
Je te suis, Rouge 3.
I’ve got a problem here.
J’ai un pépin.
– Eject! – I can hold it.
– Éjecte. – Ça va tenir !
– Pull up! – No, no, I’m all—
– Dégage-toi ! – Non, ça va bi—
The rebel base will be in firing range in seven minutes.
La base rebelle sera à portée de feu dans sept minutes.
Luke, trust your feelings.
Luke, fie-toi à ton intuition !
Squad leaders, we’ve picked up a new group of signals.
Leaders d’escadrons, on vient de capter des transmissions.
Enemy fighters coming your way.
Chasseurs ennemis en vue !
My scope’s negative. I don’t see anything.
Mon écran est négatif.
– Pick up your visual scanning. – Here they come.
– Vérifiez sur radar. – Les voilà.
Watch it. You’ve got one on your tail.
Attention ! Derrière !
I’m hit!
Je suis touché !
– You’ve picked one up! Watch it! – I can’t see it!
– Il y en a un qui te suit ! – Je ne le vois pas !
He’s on me tight. I can’t shake him!
Il me serre ! Je suis cuit !
I’ll be right there.
J’arrive !
Several fighters have broken off from the main group. Come with me.
Plusieurs engins ont changé de cap. Venez !
Pull in! Luke, pull in!
Dégagez-vous ! Luke, dégagez-vous !
Watch your back, Luke. Watch your back. Fighters above you, coming in.
Il est derrière, Luke ! Il descend sur vous !
I’m hit, but not bad. R2, see what you can do with it.
Ils m’ont eu mais c’est rien ! R2, essaie de rafistoler ça.
Hang on back there.
Au boulot !
Red Six, can you see Red Five?
Rouge 6, vous voyez Rouge 5 ?
There’s a heavy fire zone... Red Five, where are you?
Ça tire très fort par ici. Rouge 5, où êtes-vous ?
I can’t shake him!
Je peux pas le semer !
I’m on him, Luke. Hold on.
J’arrive, Luke ! Tiens bon !
Blast it, Biggs! Where are you?
Bon sang, où es-tu ?
– Thanks, Wedge. – Good shooting, Wedge.
– Merci, vieux ! – Tu as gagné la timbale !
Red Leader, this is Gold Leader. We’re starting our attack run.
Leader Rouge, ici Leader d’Or. Nous amorçons l’attaque.
I copy, Gold Leader. Move into position.
Bien compris. Mettez-vous en position.
Stay in attack formation.
Gardez la formation de combat.
The exhaust port is marked and locked in.
L’objectif est programmé sur vos écrans.
Switch all power to front deflector screens.
Plein régime sur les déflecteurs avant !
How many guns do you think, Gold Five?
Ils ont combien de canons ?
Say about 20 guns. Some on the surface, some on the towers.
Environ 20 pièces en surface et sur les tours.
Death Star will be in range in five minutes.
L’Étoile de la Mort sera à portée dans cinq minutes.
Switch to targeting computer.
Branchez les ordinateurs de visée.
Computer locked. Getting a signal.
C’est branché. J’ai déjà un signal.
The guns! They’ve stopped!
Les canons ne tirent plus !
Stabilize your rear deflectors. Watch for enemy fighters.
Stabilisez les déflecteurs arrière. Gare aux chasseurs ennemis.
They’re coming in! Three marks at 210.
Je vois trois chasseurs à 210.
– I’ll take them myself. Cover me. – Yes, sir.
– Je me charge d’eux. Couvrez-moi. – Oui, monsieur.
– It’s no good. I can’t maneuver. – Stay on target.
– Je ne tiens pas le cap ! – Restez dans l’axe !
– We’re too close.
– On est trop près !
Loosen up!
Dégagez !
Gold Five to Red Leader, lost Tiree, lost Hutch.
Or 5 à Leader Rouge. Ils ont eu Tiree et Hutch !
– I copy, Gold Leader. – They came from behind.
– Bien reçu, Leader d’Or. – Par-derrière !
We’ve analyzed their attack, sir, and there is a danger.
Nous avons analysé leur attaque, il y a un risque.
Should I have your ship standing by?
Faut-il préparer votre appareil ?
Evacuate? In our moment of triumph? I think you overestimate their chances.
Évacuer ? Au moment du triomphe ? Vous surestimez leurs chances !
Rebel base, three minutes and closing.
Base rebelle à portée de feu dans trois minutes.
Red boys, this is Red Leader. Rendezvous at mark 6.1.
Ici Leader Rouge, les gars... Rendez-vous au point 6-1.
– This is Red Two flying toward you. – Red Three standing by.
– Ici Rouge 2, j’arrive. – Rouge 3, prêt.
Red Leader, this is Base One.
Leader Rouge, ici Base Un.
Keep half your group out of range for the next run.
Attaquez avec la moitié de votre groupe.
Copy, Base One. Luke, take Red Two and Three.
Compris. Luke, dégagez avec Rouge 2 et Rouge 3.
Hold up here and wait for my signal to start your run.
Montez et attendez mon signal pour attaquer.
This is it!
Voilà l’objectif !
We should be able to see it by now.
On devrait le voir !
Keep your eyes open for those fighters.
Attention aux chasseurs !
There’s too much interference. Red Five, can you see them from where you are?
J’ai du statique ! Rouge 5, tu les vois ?
– No sign of any... Wait. Coming in .35. – I see them.
– Pas encore... Si, attends ! Ils sont au point 3-5. – Je les vois.
I’m in range.
Je suis à portée.
Target’s coming up.
L’objectif est là !
Just hold them off for a few seconds.
Tenez-les à distance un instant !
Close up formation.
Serrez la formation.
Almost there.
J’y suis presque !
– You’d better let her loose. They’re right behind me. – Almost there.
– Tirez vite ! Ils arrivent sur moi ! – J’y suis presque !
I can’t hold them.
Je ne peux pas les retenir.
It’s away!
C’est parti !
– It’s a hit! – Negative.
– Vous l’avez eu ? – Négatif !
Negative. It didn’t go in.
Négatif ! J’ai raté l’entrée.
It just impacted on the surface.
Ça a explosé à la surface.
Red Leader, we’re right above you. Turn to .05. We’ll cover for you.
Leader Rouge, on est au-dessus. Virez au point 0-5, on vous couvre.
Stay there. I just lost my starboard engine.
Restez là-haut, j’ai perdu mon moteur tribord !
Get set up for your attack run.
Préparez-vous à attaquer !
Rebel base, one minute and closing.
Base rebelle à portée de feu dans 1 minute.
Biggs, Wedge, let’s close it up. We’re going in full throttle.
Biggs ! Wedge ! Serrez, on pique.
– That ought to keep those fighters off our back. – Right with you, boss.
– Allons-y pleins gaz pour les distancer ! – On est là, patron !
Luke, at that speed, will you be able to pull out in time?
Luke ! Tu auras le temps de te dégager ?
It’ll be just like Beggar’s Canyon back home.
Le vol dans les canyons, ça me connaît !
We’ll stay back far enough to cover you.
On reste derrière pour te couvrir.
My scope shows the tower, but I can’t see the exhaust port.
Je capte la tour mais pas la bouche d’entrée !
Are you sure the computer can hit it?
Le viseur peut la situer ?
– Watch yourself. Increase speed, full throttle. – What about that tower?
– Attention ! Accélère à fond ! – Tu vois la cible ?
You worry about those fighters! I’ll worry about the tower!
Tu repères les chasseurs et moi la cible !
R2, that stabilizer’s broken loose again. See if you can’t lock it down.
R2 ! Le stabilisateur ballotte, tâche de le bloquer !
Fighters coming in .3.
Chasseurs au point 3 !
I’m hit! I can’t stay with you!
Je suis touché ! Je dois vous lâcher !
Get clear, Wedge. You can’t do any more good back there.
File. T’as plus rien à faire ici !
Sorry.
Désolé.
Let him go. Stay on the leader.
Restez sur l’engin de tête.
Hurry, Luke. They’re coming in much faster this time. We can’t hold them.
Vite, Luke, je ne peux pas les tenir !
R2, try and increase the power.
R2, monte les gaz !
Hurry up, Luke! Wait! Quick!
Dépêchez-vous ! Vite.
Rebel base, 30 seconds and closing.
Base rebelle à portée de feu dans 30 secondes.
I’m on the leader.
Je tiens le leader.
Hang on, R2.
Cramponne-toi, R2 !
Use the Force, Luke.
Fais appel à la Force, Luke !
Let go, Luke.
Laisse-la agir, Luke !
The Force is strong with this one.
Cet homme est aidé par la Force !
Luke, trust me.
Luke, aie confiance en moi !
His computer’s off.
Son ordinateur est coupé !
Luke, you switched off your targeting computer! What’s wrong?
Votre viseur est coupé ! Qu’y a-t-il ?
Nothing. I’m all right.
Rien du tout. Tout va bien.
I’ve lost R2!
Ils ont eu R2 !
The Death Star has cleared the planet.
L’Étoile de la Mort a contourné la planète.
– Rebel base in range. – You may fire when ready.
– Base rebelle à portée. – Vous pouvez ouvrir le feu !
Commence primary ignition.
Déclenchez la mise à feu !
I have you now.
Je te tiens !
– What? – Yahoo!
Quoi ?
Look out!
Attention.
You’re all clear, kid! Now let’s blow this thing and go home!
La voie est dégagée. Fais péter ça et on rentre !
Stand by.
Paré à tirer.
Great shot, kid! That was one in a million!
Bien joué, p’tit gars ! Dans le mille !
Remember, the Force will be with you always.
Souviens-toi... La Force sera avec toi... à tout jamais !
I knew you’d come back. I just knew it.
J’étais sûr que tu reviendrais !
Well, I wasn’t going to let you get all the credit and take all the reward.
Je voulais pas te laisser toutes les médailles !
Hey, I knew there was more to you than money.
Je savais que l’argent n’était pas tout pour vous !
– Oh, no! – Oh, my. R2, can you hear me?
– Oh, non. – C’est atroce ! R2, tu m’entends ?
Say something. You can repair him, can’t you?
Parle-moi ! On pourra le réparer, n’est-ce pas ?
– We’ll get to work on him right away. – You must repair him.
– On s’en occupe tout de suite. – Il faut le réparer !
Sir, if any of my circuits or gears will help, I’ll gladly donate them.
Qu’on lui greffe mes circuits si ça peut l’aider !
He’ll be all right.
Il va s’en sortir !